<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>England's beauty in seeing King Charles the Second restored to majesty preached by Tho. Reeve ... in the parish church of Waltham Abbey in the county of Essex.</title>
            <author>Reeve, Thomas, 1594-1672.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 168 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58343</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R688</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R33981</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13646910</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13646910</idno>
            <idno type="VID">100932</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58343)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 100932)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1045:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>England's beauty in seeing King Charles the Second restored to majesty preached by Tho. Reeve ... in the parish church of Waltham Abbey in the county of Essex.</title>
                  <author>Reeve, Thomas, 1594-1672.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 59 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I.R. for the authour,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685 --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:100932:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100932:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ENGLAND'S BEAUTY In ſeeing KING CHARLES the SECOND Reſtored to MAJESTY.</p>
            <p>Preached by THO. REEVE. D. D. in the Pariſh Church of <hi>Waltham-Abbey</hi> in the County of <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>I have broken the bonds of your yoake, and made you goe upright.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Levit. 26.13.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>In that day will I raiſe up the Tabernacle of <hi>David,</hi> that is fallen, and cloſe up the breaches thereof, and I will raiſe up the ruines thereof, and will build it as in the dayes of old.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Amos 9.11.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Surſum verſus ſacrorum fluminum feruntur fontes.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Euripid.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by I. R. for the Authour, 1661</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:100932:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:100932:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the most Potent, and Puiſſant</hi> MONARCH CHARLES the II. KING of GREAT BRITAIN, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>DREAD SOVERAIGN,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>OD hath given us a <hi>Sight,</hi> the <hi>Sight</hi> of your <hi>Self.</hi> How many aking eyes where there once to ſee You? how many ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhed eyes may there be now to behold You? Every one could not preſent ſuch a <hi>Sight;</hi> no, He in Heaven,</p>
            <q>
               <pb facs="tcp:100932:3"/>
               <hi>Reſtituit Patriis Androgeona focis,</hi>
            </q>
            <p>Hath reſtored You to your Fathers Throne to be looked upon as a glorious <hi>Spectacle.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Propert. l. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> We ſaw for many years nothing but the horrid faces of ſtrange Rulers, and now we have your Face of true Majeſty to bleſs our eyes with,</p>
            <q>
               <l>—forma tum vertitur oris</l>
               <l>Antiquum in Buten,<note place="margin">Virg. Ae. neid. <hi>9.</hi>
                  </note> —</l>
            </q>
            <p>Oh that we had good eyes in our heads to diſcern the difference of Objects; what a change is this, that whereas we ſaw nothing but Uſurpers in their <hi>Barbarouſneſſe, Our eyes do now ſee a King in his Beautie?</hi> Your abſence was the <hi>Bane,</hi> Your preſence is the <hi>Beautie</hi> of the Nation. To apply all this <hi>Beautie</hi> to Your Self, perhaps would be judged flattery, therefore have I endeavoured to ſhew Your three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, that there is a derivative Beauty in You, namely that your <hi>Majeſtie</hi> is our <hi>Beautie.</hi> For how is a Nation obſcured if it hath not a King in it? and how is it illuſtred, if it hath a King reigning in Royal Splendour and Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial dignity? I wiſh that there be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Iudges of <hi>Beautie</hi> in the Land, and that there be none which are ready to ſtrike at the face of <hi>Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</hi> It doth grieve me, that when you have
<pb facs="tcp:100932:3"/>brought delight to the eyes of Millions, and put peace into all hands, yet that there ſhould be left amongſt us ſome glaring eyes, and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacing hands, The Jeſuit to ſuch may reſigne his malicious eyes, and miſchievous hands. What need thoſe King-vexers and Gad-flyes of Monarchs plot treaſons, and kindle diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, when we have Incendiaries, and State<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troublers of our own?</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Ab pudeat, certe pudeat.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Propert l. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> —</q>
            <p>For is it not an infamy that a Reformed Church ſhould agree with the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in the Gun-room? that men ſhould caſt out Popery at the portal, and take it in at the poſterne? Which of theſe are the better Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject?</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Arcades ambo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Horat.</note>
            </q>
            <p>Both of them can level at Kings. For the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of religion then theſe muſt ever hereafter lay aſide diſſentions, and lay down armes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Kings, or elſe there will not onely be the treacherous and fatal Jeſuit, but the odious and omirous Proteſtant. For conſcience ſake therefore I truſt a King ſhall not need to fear a frighting or a fighting Proteſtant. For muſt a face of Majeſty ſmile upon all Deſigners,
<pb facs="tcp:100932:4"/>or <hi>Beauty</hi> eſpouſe it ſelf to every Corrival, or elſe ſhall there be weapons drawn to force fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour and affection? this is bad morality, and worſe divinity. For where did they learn this? ſure I am not in Scripture, for that ſaith <hi>Fear God, and honour the King, and I advertiſe thee to take heed to the Kings Commandment, and that in reſpect of the Oath of God.</hi> Therefore men muſt ſeem to have no reverence to Gods lawes, nor dread of perjury, or elſe their brains muſt leave plotting, and their hands leave braining. They may find theſe grounds of conſpiracy in old Achitophel, or new Mariana, but confident I am, that they cannot in the Old Teſtament, or the new. Except then they would burn their Bibles, and make Humour their Holy writ they muſt conſume to aſhes ſuch principles and practiſes. We have been ſhamed enough farre and nigh for ſuch paradoxes and ſtrata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gemes, and curſed be they which do renew the next ſcandal. The honour of the Church, and the <hi>Beauty</hi> of the Kingdome are then gone. Have Proteſtants againſt Papiſts ſheathed up their ſwords, and ſhall Proteſtants againſt Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants unſheath theirs? what againſt their fellow Profeſſours? what againſt their natural
<pb facs="tcp:100932:4"/>King? oh inexorable, oh incorrigible King-haters? Men have been mad, and ſome diſtempers we have lately found, but ſurely this phrenzy will not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes laſt. Let them look your Majeſty through, and what occaſion can they find in you of diſguſt, diſtaſt, or ſo much as diſcontent? So far as I can perceive your Majeſty doth but ſeek your Native Right, the eſtabliſhed Religion, the fundamental Lawes, the Honour of the Higheſt, the freedome of the meaneſt, the welfare of the Nation, the Peace of the Kingdome, and they may ſee as well as I that your graces are conſpicuous, your qualifications e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent, your carriage affable, your Government mild, your counſailes prudent, your actions Heroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, your life ſpotleſs, and your conſcience ſincere, except therefore they would have an Angel to reign over them, where can they have in fleſh and blood a more deſired man? what heart then can have a rancorous thought againſt ſuch a King? No, I hope to ſee all your Enemies bluſh at their cauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs anger, and ſenſeleſs ſpight; yea to fall down at your Royall Feet, and repent that they have been ſo inconſiderate, and weep that they have been ſo unkind. Bear but with their former failings, &amp; par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don that which is paſt (as what cannot that Royal Heart of Yours that is the living ſpring of clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy
<pb facs="tcp:100932:5"/>waſh out of your remembrance?) and me think your Majeſty ſhould have felt the laſt of animoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and triumphs; people will not alwayes kick againſt the pricks, and run upon the ſpeares ſpoint of divine lawes, but do that which God hath obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged them to, even honour your Perſon, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge your Authority, ſubmit to your Edicts, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire your Perfections, and be knit to you in the adamantine chains of Fidelity and Loyalty, that this waſted Country may once again become a flouriſhing Nation, and the Kingdom of Triumphs. Thus in all Humility proſtrating my Self at your Majeſties Royal Feet, and Praying for your long Life, your increaſe of Princely Honours, your laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Peace, and everlaſting Bliſſe, ſubmiſſively I take leave, and reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Majeſties <hi>Devoted Subject in all unſtained, and inviolable Loyalty</hi> THO. REEVE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:100932:5"/>
            <head>ENGLAND'S BEAUTY.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Eſay 33.17.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Thine eyes ſhall ſee the King in his Beauty.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ere is <hi>Senacherib</hi> in a fury, and <hi>Hezekiah</hi> in a fray; <hi>Senacherib</hi> was guilty of much rapine, and he would authorize his robberies under Gods broad ſeale; for thus ſaith his Commiſſioner General, <hi>Am I now come up without the Lord against this place to destroy it? the Lord ſaid to me, Go up against this Land, and deſtroy it.</hi> 2 Kings 18.25. ſo that, prey is piety, and rapacity is religion, the Lords name muſt be the Patent to the moſt injurious courſes in the world. The Lords cauſe, and the Lords Commiſſion, the Lords banners, and booties muſt be cried up in the moſt ſavage depredations. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacherib</hi>'s hoſt is conſecrated by <hi>Rabſhakeh</hi> to be an Army of Saints, this ſame hallowing of Camps (where ſouldiers diverſe times are little better then Scorpions) is but an old Paradoxe of Rabſhakchs military Divinity; that as the old Sequeſtratours, or Seiſers upon Delinquents eſtates, caſt men out of their houſes, and ſaid, <hi>Let God be glorified</hi> Eſ. 66.5; So theſe in the fear of God, and by the impulſe of the Spirit change governments, behead Kings, plunder Countries, and cut throats. Did not the Lord ſet them on work? Did they any thing but by a call from Heaven? every ſharking Trooper can ſay,</p>
            <q>
               <l>— mihi Phoebus Apollo<note place="margin">Virg. <hi>3.</hi> Aeneid.</note>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Praedixit,</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <p>I am taught from above to act as I do. What cauſe had <hi>Sanache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rib</hi> to invade, or infeſt Jury? cauſe? Highway-mans provocation; he had a mind to take a purſe, and this was all the offence which
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:100932:6"/>he could pretend. He harraſſed an innocent Nation without the leaſt grievance, for <hi>Wo be to thee which ſpoyledſt, and wert not ſpoyled, and dealst treacherouſly, when thou wert not dealt treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly with;</hi> v. 1. But the ſword is drawn, what ſhall ſheath it up? ſhall parley? no, oppreſſion is too venemous a Cockatrice to be thus charmed; <hi>Senacherib</hi> is deaf to all Accommodation, he muſt be his own Arbitratour, or elſe no pacification will be conſented to. Meſſengers are ſent, but they might have ſtayd at home, Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours are diſpatched, but</p>
            <q>— rapiunt conamina venti,<note place="margin">Stat. <hi>6.</hi> Theb.</note>
            </q>
            <p>They do but poure their treaties into the ayre, they do return not with articles of agreement in their hands, but with briniſh tears in their eyes. <hi>Behold the Meſſengers ſhall cry without, the Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours ſhall weep bitterly.</hi> v. 7. And what then are the conſequents of this fruitleſſe mediation? what but wofull skars? Reſolve ſuch an implacable enemy,</p>
            <q>Venturum excidio Lybiae, —</q>
            <p>To come to the utter deſtruction of the Land. Then have at Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellers, Merchants, Nobles, Monuments, Kings Palaces, Kings Parks, Kings Woods, neither highwayes, ſtreets, fields, forreſts are free from danger. There is nothing to be ſeen all the Country over, but the rufulleſt face of miſery, that mans eye could behold. Rabſhakeh ſaid, that he did come from God, but if all the <hi>Eume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nides</hi> had made him Captain General, could he have been the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour of more diſmal outrages? No place, right, calling, covenant, matter, or man were regarded; for <hi>The high-wayes lay wast, the way-faring man ceaſeth, he hath broken the Covenant, he hath deſpiſed Cities, he regardeth no man, and the earth mourneth, and languiſheth, Lebanon is aſhamed and hewen down, Sharon is like a wilderneſs, and Baſhan, and Carmel ſhake off their fruits.</hi> v. 8.9. Calamity enough, but is this miſery endleſs? No, God whoſe name had been abuſed, his covenant violated and his people oppreſſed, at laſt doth look down upon their ruthes, and riſe up for their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe, <hi>Now will I riſe ſaith the Lord, now will I be exalted, now will I lift up myſelf.</hi> V. 10. Though a long time their contrive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments had been ſuccesfull, yet at laſt their policies ſhould be ſnares, and their deſigns fetters, yea, they ſhould but kindle a fire to burn their ſelves to aſhes, for ye <hi>ſhall conceive chaffe, and bring forth
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:100932:6"/>ſtubble, your breath as fire ſhall devour you. The people ſhall be as the burning of lime, as thornes cut up ſhall they be burns in the fire.</hi> V. 11.12. yea the judgement ſhall be ſo terrible, that it ſhall be the bruit of the earth,</p>
            <q>Rumor it, &amp; magnum ſermonibus occupat orbem,<note place="margin">Ovid. <hi>6.</hi> Met.</note>
            </q>
            <p>For <hi>Hear ye that are far off, what I have done, and ye that are near acknowledge my might.</hi> V. 13. It's true, Temporizers and Neuters had ſad apprehenſions, as if this dolefull ſtare could never be altered, they cry out,</p>
            <q>Funditus occidimus, nec habet fortuna regreſſum.<note place="margin">Virg. <hi>11.</hi> Aeneid.</note>
            </q>
            <p>We are utterly undone, and the proſperity of the Nation can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have a return; the fire is kindled, and all will be conſumed in this waſting flame. <hi>The ſinners in Sion ſhall be afraid, fearfulneſſe hath ſurpriſed the hypocrites. Who amongst us ſhall dwell with the devouring fire? who amongst us ſhall dwell with the everlasting burnings?</hi> V. 14. But ſhall there be no more auſpicious thing to be expected by the righteous? yes, they that have not wavered in this time of tryal, but have done, and ſpoken that which do become true Patriots, and ſincere Profeſſouts, which neither were diſmayed with accidents, nor have followed the hurſe in State, not lurched any thing out of the common caſualty, nor brained men with the pole-axe of the age, but had lived like ſteady, invariable, &amp; incorrupt perſons, not skilled in the pinching, and bribing arts of the times, but tender over mens eſtates, and bloud, theſe men ſhall have ample, and ſtable felicity, for <hi>He that walketh righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, and hath ſpoken uprightly, he that deſpiſeth the gaine of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, and hath ſhaken his hands from taking of bribes, that ſtoppeth his cares from hearing of blond, and ſhutteth his eyes from ſeeing of evill, He ſhall dwell on high, his place ſhall be the muni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of rocks, bread ſhall be given him, and his waters ſhall be ſure.</hi> V. 15.16. Well, here are pledges for the peoples happineſſe, but what newes for the King? What muſt he alwayes live in ſtreights? no, his enemies ſhall be diſperſed ſtrangely, and he in a miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous manner reſtored. <hi>Senacherib</hi> came in upon the ſpurre, but he ſhall be drawn back with a hook. <hi>Senacherib</hi> ſhall vaniſh, and <hi>Hezekiah</hi> ſhall appear; He ſhall be looked upon as a King, and as a King in pomp and ſplendour, the age ſhall be raviſhed to ſee his Majeſtick eſtate, and be in a trance to ſee a depreſſed Prince
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:100932:7"/>raiſed up to the height of ſublime dignity, for they ſhall not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>ſee him a King, but a King in his Beauty. Thine eyes ſhall ſee the King in his Beauty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the Text conſider with me,</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <label>1. The opening of a Cabinet, or a clear manifeſtation,</label>
                     <hi>Thine eyes ſhall ſee</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>2. The Gemme preſented,</label>
                     <hi>The King</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <label>3. The luſtre of the ſame,</label>
                     <hi>In his Beauty.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, for the opening of the Cabinet, or the clear manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Thine eyes ſhall ſee.</hi> Gods Cabinet had been ſhut, but he would unlock it, people had lived in the dark, and though they might hope for much, yet for the preſent they diſcerned nothing, but this black sky ſhould not alwayes laſt, there ſhould come a time of light and ſight, though thy eyes do not ſee, yet thine eyes ſhall ſee. <hi>Thine eyes ſhall ſee.</hi> From hence obſerve, that <hi>the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of a bleſſing is in the actual fruition of the ſame,</hi> not to have it promiſed, but preſented, not hoped for, but enjoyed.</p>
            <q>— long a mora est nobis,<note place="margin">Ovid.</note> quae gaudia differt,</q>
            <p>Retarding, which doth delay a bleſſing, is very irkſome to us,</p>
            <q>— <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Homer. Iliad. 2.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,</q>
            <p>To expect long, and at laſt to return empty is tedious, and vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.<note place="margin">Petrarch. dial. <hi>110.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Nunquam expectatio tranquillitaſque ſimul cohabitant.</hi> Long waiting, and ſatisfaction do never dwell together. <hi>The hope that is deferred doth afflict the ſoul. The brests of conſolation yield us no ſweetneſſe, till we milk out, and be delighted with the abundance of glory.</hi> Eſ. 66.11. Eſpouſals do not ſatisfy a bride, but actual wedding. The Iſraelites had many a ſad grone till they entred the Land of Canaan, and <hi>Noah</hi> till the Arke reſted upon the Mountains of Ararat. <hi>Better is the ſight of the eyes, then the wandring of the deſire.</hi> Eccleſ. 6.9. The wandring of the deſires is pain, and grief, but the ſeeing with the eyes is contentment, therefore <hi>David</hi> praiſed God that <hi>he ſet one upon his Throne, his eyes ſeeing it.</hi> 1 Kings 1.48. And God did comfort up his dear people,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.5.</note> that <hi>their eyes ſhould ſee, that God would be magnified from the border of Iſrael.</hi> Senſible comforts are moſt ſatisfactory,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:100932:7"/>not thoſe which have their prediction, but their production, ſuch as are come to an accompliſhment, and are brought to eye-ſight. <hi>Thine eyes ſhall ſee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. This doth ſhew firſt that <hi>God is the God of ſights,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Appl.</note> 
               <hi>the thing that is hid he can bring forth to light.</hi> Job 28.11. <hi>He can ſhew wonders in the Heavens, and the Earth.</hi> Joel 2.28. yea ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light our eares, and affect our eyes, that we ſhall ſtand in a kind of amazement, and ſay, <hi>Who hath heard ſuch a thing? and who hath ſeen ſuch things.</hi> Eſ. 66.8. <hi>How great are his ſignes? how mighty are his wonders?</hi> Dan. 4.3. oh then we that are all for rare things, and ſtrange ſights, why do we not cleave cloſe to God? is there any which can ſo dazle our eyes? Is not he the God of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects? yes, he is the great <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Wonder-worker,<note place="margin">Naz. Hugo de Operat. trium die<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</note> 
               <hi>dedit o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culis, quod vix comprehendere potest oculus.</hi> He hath given ſo much to the eye, that the eye cannot comprehend it. If we would be Spectatours of bright things, then we ſhould never ſeparate our ſelves from him who doth make every thing to ſhine with radiant beames, no, we ſhould <hi>frui Deo, ſicut luce oculus,</hi> enjoy God,<note place="margin">Aug. l. <hi>2.</hi> de Civit. Dei c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> as the eye doth the light. If we <hi>provoke the eyes of his glory,</hi> he will vex our eyes with ſad ſights, but if we do that which is acceptable in his eyes, he will do that, which ſhall be delectable to our eyes. We are enemies to the joy of our lives, and not worth the eyes in our heads, which do incenſe God; for this is that which do hinder us from many glorious things, which we might behold. Doth God uſually tranſport the wicked? no, they ſcarce ſee an admirable thing in their life-time; the extaſying ſights are for the righteous, they are the pure eyes which ſee raviſhments, God doth reſerve his prime Objects for his <hi>Hidden Ones,</hi> for them that are unto him as the apple of his eye, or cleanſed eyes, let us then be the pleaſure of his eyes, becauſe he is the God of our Objects; it is he that ſaith, I will delight thy ſenſes, it is he that ſaith, <hi>Thine eyes ſhall ſee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, this doth ſhew us that we may depend upon God for wonders, <hi>the eyes of all things look upon thee,</hi> and they may, for he is the God of the eyes, and hath the curious, and marvellous ſights for them. The pictures with orient colours do hang in his gallery, the exquiſite, poliſhed, elaborate maſter-pieces are to be ſeen in his Providence. <hi>Totus manus est,</hi> He is all hand.<note place="margin">Aug.</note> 
               <hi>Deus in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:100932:8"/>una existentia omnia praehabet.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dionyſ. de Div. nom. l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi> Aquin. <hi>1.</hi> a. q. <hi>4.</hi> a. <hi>2.</hi> Roet.</note> God in his one exiſtency hath the anticipation of all things which can be ſhewn. <hi>Totam perfectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem eſſendi in ſe continet.</hi> He doth include the perfection of every being in himſelf. For other things it may be ſaid that <hi>unumquod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que est bonum ſuo bono,</hi> Every thing is good by his own proper and particular good, but God hath goodneſſe in him not by way of limitation, determination, order, ſpecies, or meaſure; but by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diviſion, eminency, and exceſſe, he being the Abſtract of all the concrete excellencies in the world,<note place="margin">Dionyſ. de Divin. nom. l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi> Hilar. l. <hi>8.</hi> de Tria. Aug. in Enchir. c. <hi>10.</hi> hom. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> for he is not <hi>hoc, aut hoc, ſed omnia,</hi> this, or that, but all things. He is <hi>immenſae virtutis vivens, &amp; potens,</hi> The living, and powerfull thing of an unlimited virtue. There is in God <hi>univerſitatis admirabilis pulchritudo,</hi> the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable beauty of the whole univerſe, therefore thoſe things which come from him are not onely good, but <hi>valde bona, very good.</hi> God then can ſhew us better things, and greater things, and brighter things, then ever we yet beheld. If potent man (as thou thinkeſt) can make thee ſee ſtrange things, what can the Omnipotent God? he can preſent to thee <hi>terrible things</hi> (that is, admirable things) <hi>which thou lookedſt not for,</hi> even fill thy eyes with <hi>Wonders;</hi> that thou ſhalt ſay, <hi>whence come theſe Objects? who ever thought to have ſeen ſuch things? oh the mysteries of Divine Providence! oh the ſplendour of Gods actings! The like was never ſeen in Iſrael.</hi> Mat. 9.33. <hi>they were all amazed, and glorified God, ſaying, we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſaw it on this ſort.</hi> Mark 2.12. <hi>Who is like unto thee oh Lord amongst the Gods? who is like unto thee, glorious in holineſſe, fearfull in praiſes, doing wonders?</hi> Exod. 15.11. As if there were not in the whole world tongues lowd enough to ſing out Gods praiſes, or eyes bright enough to ſee the admiration which ſhine in his works. When thou ſeeſt nothing but tears, God can make thee ſee triumphs; when thou ſeeſt nothing but Chains, God can make thee ſee Crowns; when thou ſeeſt nothing but Wounds, God can make thee ſee Wonders. He is not onely <hi>Jehovah-Shalom, the Lord our Peace.</hi> Judg. 6.24. or <hi>Jehovah-Niſſi, the Lord our Banner, but Jehovah-Jireh, our ſeeing God, or the God that will foreſee for us, for the Lord ſeeth, or will ſee for us.</hi> What ſhalt thou not ſee, if the Lord will but ſay, <hi>Thine eyes ſhall ſee?</hi> Thou ſhalt ſee a change of all thy miſeries, an end of all thy tryals, all thy old diſaſters are gone, God will create all things <hi>new things.</hi> Iſ. 43.19.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:100932:8"/>and call thee by a <hi>new name.</hi> Iſ. 62.2. and <hi>build new gates to the Houſe of the Lord.</hi> Jer. 26.10. and unto the Jewes ſhall ariſe a <hi>new light, and joy, and gladneſſe, and honour.</hi> Eſter. 8.16. let not the faces of thy preſent enemies too much daunt thee, for <hi>the Aegy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptians whom thou hast ſeen to day, thou ſhalt ſee no more here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</hi> Exod. 14.13. Let not the afflicted condition of profeſſion too much perplexe thee, for thou ſhalt ſee <hi>Jehoſhuah</hi> put off his fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy garments, and behold a fair Diademe ſet upon his head, and rich garments put upon his back. Zach. 3.4.5. Let not the ſcattered ſtones of Sion too much trouble thee, for thou ſhalt <hi>ſee Sion have her ſtones laid with Carbuncles, and her foundations with Saphirs, her very windows ſhall be made of Emeralds, and all her gates of ſhining ſtones.</hi> Iſ. 54.11.12. thou ſhalt <hi>ſee Jeruſalem a quiet habitation, the City of ſolemnities, and ſet up as the praiſe of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi> Talk not too much of the bloud, and hunger, and flavery which have been endured in the Nation, for <hi>ye ſhall not ſee the ſword, and famine, and yoak any more;</hi> be not ſo much dejected to ſee the lamp of religion even extinguiſhed, for <hi>what ſeest thou? and I ſaid I looked, and behold, a Candleſtick all of gold, and a bowle upon the top of it, and ſeven lamps, and ſeven pipes to the lamps, and two olive trees, the one on the right ſide of the bowle, and the other on the left ſide of the bowle to empty themſelves into the pipes.</hi> Zach. 4.2.3. After a grievous deſolation, there may be a glorious reſtauration; after thou haſt ſeen as ſad ſights as mans eyes can look upon, thou maiſt ſee as chearing, delightfull ſights as mans eyes can behold; thou maiſt ſee a new face, a new faſhion, a new form, a new frame, a new Church, a new State, God may bring forth <hi>the firſt Dominion, raiſe up the Tabernacle of David that is fallen, cloſe up breaches, and build it as in the dayes of old.</hi> Amos 9.11. ſhe that was called <hi>Deſolate, Forſaken,</hi> may be called <hi>Hephzibah, Beulah, my Delight is in her, or my amiable ſpouſe.</hi> Iſ. 62.4. ſhe that hath been quenched to the laſt ſpark may prove <hi>a firebrand in the ſheaf.</hi> Zach. 12.6. ſhe that hath been drunken with miſeries may turn to <hi>be a cup of poyſon to all them that are round about her.</hi> Zach. 12.2. ſhe <hi>that have lain amongst the pots may have ſilver wings given her, and feathers like gold.</hi> Pſ. 68.13. Sion that hath been beaten with inſtruments of iron may <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe and threſh.</hi> Micah 4.13. Jeruſalem that lay in the duſt may
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:100932:9"/>have <hi>her old old waſt places repaired, &amp; foundations laid for many generations.</hi> Eſ. 58.12. When the Sun of a Churches proſperity hath paſt the Meridian line, and it is even about to ſet, yet God can <hi>make the ſhadowes to return back many degrees,</hi> as he did up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Dyal of <hi>Ahaz;</hi> when a grievous drought hath remained many years amongſt the Saints, God can make a little cloud to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, and though at firſt it be no bigger then a mans hand, yet in time it may overſpread the whole heavens, and there may follow after it a great raine, as it happened in the dayes of <hi>Achab;</hi> we have never ſeen our laſt of favours, if God pleaſeth not to reſtrain his Providence: for when our hand is paſt working, can Gods hand effect nothing? yes, <hi>Ariſe, ariſe, put on ſtrength oh Arm of the Lord, ariſe as in the old time, as in the generations that are paſt. Art not thou the ſame that cut in pieces Rahab? and wounded the Dragon?</hi> Iſ. 51.9. God cannot be maſtered with the greateſt difficulty, all State-tricks, and politick deſignes are to him but as rotten cords, and ſpiders webs. <hi>Knowest thou not me, ſaith the Lord? The Lord is a man of war, his name is Jehovah.</hi> Exod. 15.3. Oh he, which meaſure the waters in-his fiſt, ſpan the heavens, comprehend the duſt of the earth in a meaſure, weigh the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains in ſcales, and the hils in a balance, which doth dry up rivers, cleave the rocks, break the heads of the Dragons, which doth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count all the Inhabitants of the earth but as graſhoppers to him, and doth but look upon the earth, and he maketh it to tremble, what can reſiſt his will? or oppoſe his power? no, after thou haſt ſpent out a life in groanes and tears, he can adom thee with ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brets; after thou haſt been waſted with wars, and thine own dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling-place hath caſt thee out, he can lead thee into thine own houſe, and make thee ſit under thine own vine, and thine own figge-tree in peace. Rely upon this God then, and expect Wonders from him; when thy eye-bals have aked to behold any thing that is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable, and nothing thou couldſt diſcern, though thy eyes were ready <hi>to fall out.</hi> Deut. 28.65. yet then he may tell thee that happy ſights are at hand, yea ſay unto thee, <hi>Thine eyes ſhall ſee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, this doth ſhew that <hi>God is to have the honour of all rich bleſſings. Doth this appertain to man?</hi> 2 Sam. 7.19. to man to gratify the world with ſights? no, it is God onely that ſaith,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:100932:9"/>
               <hi>thine eyes ſhall ſee.</hi> Oh then that we are apt to turn our eyes the wrong way, even to fixe them upon man, rather then God! For man we ſee, and think that by him we onely ſee, that none preſents ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to our eyes, but this Inferiour Deity. Thus we commit Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try with theſe petty-gods, and ſacrifice to theſe earthly Numens; as if we would bury all the honour of happy things in duſt-heaps, or make the Sun-glaſſe more excellent then the Sun it ſelf. This hath been mans dim ſight ever to ſee nothing but the face be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us, or to magnify the ſtream in ſtead of the Spring-head, ſo that whereas we ſhould adore God, we have <hi>mens perſons in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration.</hi> Jude 11. and for giving him in Heaven the juſt glory of all his free favours we beſtow upon men <hi>flattering titles.</hi> Job 32.22. whereby in ſtead of aſcribing praiſe to the true Authour of our felicity, we deify the Creature; this hath alwayes been mans vanity, or rather impiety to worſhip at the wrong Altar, or ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to our own nets, and to burn incenſe to our own yame, juſt as <hi>Helleſpontius</hi> who would needs have <hi>Xerxes</hi> to be <hi>Jupiter</hi> in the ſhape of a Perſian, or the Athenians,<note place="margin">Herod. l. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> who becauſe <hi>Demetrius Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liorcetes</hi> won <hi>Munychia</hi> from <hi>Caſſander,</hi> whereby they were freed from the Macedonian tyranny,<note place="margin">Sabell. l. <hi>7.</hi> Ennead. <hi>4.</hi> Cuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian.</note> would needs have him received into the number of the gods, and appointed a particular Prieſt to ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to him, ſaying, that he was the onely god to them that was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waken, and all the reſt of the gods were aſleep; and <hi>Tribonian,</hi> who becauſe <hi>Justinian</hi> had been very ſuccesfull in all his enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſes called him an immortal creature, promiſing him that he ſhould never dye, but carry his fleſh with him into heaven. But when man hath plaid the Paraſite never ſo long with his fellow-creature, is it man that is the principal Agent? no, God knows, he cannot of himſelf <hi>make one hair white, or black.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. <hi>10.16.</hi> Calv. in <hi>2.</hi> Hoſ. Bern. Socrates.</note> God is ſuch an abſolute <hi>former of all things,</hi> that <hi>ne pluviae gutta è coelo cadat niſi ſuo nutu, not a drop of rain can fall out of the clouds, but by his appointment;</hi> therefore of all bleſſings <hi>Deus auctor, &amp; fautor, God is the Founder, and Foſterer.</hi> What then? ſhall man be wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped? no <hi>Thus diis, Incenſe both belong to God, it is the good will of him that dwelt in the buſh.</hi> Deut. 33.16. which doth make every thing proſperous to us. Set aſide Gods aſſiſtance; what can the feeble arm of man do? no, <hi>He hath wrought all our works for us.</hi> Iſ. 26.12. <hi>I will magnify my ſelf (ſaith the Lord) and Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:100932:10"/>my ſelf, and will be known in all Nations.</hi> Ezech. 28.23. <hi>In thine hand is power and ſtrength, and in thine hand it is to make great, and to give ſtrength unto all.</hi> 1 Chron. 29.12. Can we ſee any thing of our ſelves, till God hold a bleſſing to our eyes? no, <hi>When God ſhall bring again Sion, then ſhall they ſee eye to eye,</hi> Iſ. 52.8. Then, and not till then. Here then is your Architectoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Agent, therefore we ought <hi>to aſcribe greatneſſe to him.</hi> Deut. 32.3. and <hi>ſpeak of the glorious honour of his Majeſty, and his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drous works.</hi> Pſ. 145.5. For will God ever endure any to ſit in his Throne, and weare his Crown? no, he made <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> to go graze amongſt the beaſts for this, and for this he threw Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifer out of Heaven. Away then with the cryes, and ingeminated praiſes that are given to men, let not theſe be ſo much as ſpoken of, till God hath had the firſt ſong, the new ſong, and his ſong of degrees; praiſe not man at all, till ye have praiſed God in the Higheſt; no, let God have his Hymnes before Man hath his Pane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyricks; And thus indeed, when God hath had his worſhip, man may have his honour, for man is Gods Subſtitute, or Delegate, whereby Bleſſings are conveyed, therefore we may bleſſe theſe in God, or under God; we are not to make them Gods, but we may make them Gods ſerviceable Deputies; howſoever we muſt remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber to give the prime and principal reverence, veneration and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doration to God, becauſe man cannot ſhew us a ſight, nor bring to our view (of himſelf) the leaſt thing, which can delight and affect the eye-ſight, no, it is God onely, that doth ſay, and can ſay, <hi>Thine eyes ſhall ſee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, this doth exhort us to wait patiently for Gods pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting of Objects; for he doth not ſay thine eyes do ſee, but <hi>Thine eyes ſhall ſee.</hi> God obſerveth his own moments for bleſſings, his hand of bounty muſt not be wreſted, nor his bowels of compaſſion wrung;<note place="margin">Per. Ser. <hi>9.</hi> ſuper Qui habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat. Greg. hom. <hi>35.</hi> in Evang. cum au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieritis. p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alia.</note> are favours to be compelled? or gratuities conſtrained? no, this is immodeſty, a paſſion upon compaſſion. <hi>Quicquid toleran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, quicquid operandum, pondus diei, &amp; aeſtus ſuſtinenda ſunt.</hi> Every thing is to be endured, every thing waited for, we muſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo the heat, &amp; burthen of the day before we catch at a bleſſing. A ſteady Profeſſour, if he cannot have his deſires inſtantly ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, <hi>non proruat ad exceſſum murmurationis,</hi> muſt not break out into the exceſſe of murmuring. Accelerating deſires are ill guides
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:100932:10"/>ſaid <hi>Socrates,</hi> raſh deſires are as bad as raſh ſouldiers,<note place="margin">Liv. <hi>3,</hi> Decad. l. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Feſtinatio improvida est &amp; caeca.</hi> Too much ſpeed is both improvident, and blind; therefore ſaith the faithfull, <hi>We haved waited for the in the way of thy judgements.</hi> Iſ. 26.8. that is they were not too ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to have the judgement over till God thought it fit. <hi>As the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandman doth wait for the precious fruits of the earth,</hi> ſo ſhould we for Gods precious favours. We muſt not rip up the dugge for milk, not force the child out of the womb till the hour of delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance be come, not launch forth till the tide be come in, not deſire to taſt of fruits till Gods Sun-beams have ripened them; a fair hand muſt be written leiſurely, a curious picture is long in the drawing; it is the torment of religion to be too paſſionate upon bleſſings, they are ſick Chriſtians which are wiſhing for light before the day-ſtarre do appear. True Saints hatch mercies, and do not deſire to hear the bird chirping, till the ſhell be broken; and they endure their winter-agues patiently, till the running of the bloud at ſpring-tide. None entertain favours with more fervour, nor expect them with more faith. And this is according to the rule, for <hi>He that believeth ſhall not make haſte.</hi> Iſ. 28.16. It is a tumult againſt Heaven to wiſh to be happy before Gods time, theſe unſeaſonable deſires are both irrational, and irreligious. Such importunate ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors are troubled with <hi>Rachels</hi> impatience, who muſt have chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren at her own call, or elſe ſhe is ready to dye. Theſe are thoſe which would drink wine out of the green cluſters, or be eſpouſed to Gods favours before the Virgins are marriageable: But can God endure ſuch a rape upon his bleſſings? or that men ſhould break open the doors upon him for an almes? Theſe are ſturdy Beggars indeed, and fitter to be carried to the whipping-poſt, then to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Boones. The ſtill child doth deſerve two breads, but the cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morous child doth ſcarcely deſerve to be fed at all. Wraſtle as much as ye will for bleſſings, but do not ſeek to get them with chiding and raving; that is a bad tongue which is ſtridulent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, which would make him a Debtour rather then a Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. Thou muſt endure to have thy faith to be tried, as well as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to have thy wants ſupplyed; thou muſt live with expectation, till Gods time of exhibition come; for <hi>the Viſion is yet for an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed time, though it tarry, wait.</hi> Habbac. 2.3. It is a <hi>ſin to limit the Holy one of Iſrael.</hi> Pſ. 78.41. to confine God to our own ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:100932:11"/>or punctilioes. As if God muſt feed us according to our own appetites, or elſe we are ſtarved, or he muſt deliver us when we call for freedome, or elſe <hi>he does put a ſword into our enemies hands to ſlay us.</hi> Exod. 5.21. Is not this the general cry, we are not helped, we ſhall not be helped; we do not ſee, we ſhall not ſee? yes, then the caſe is remedileſſe, all is given over, as loſt. Oh what adoe had we not long ſince to quiet the penſive! and to ſilence the diſcontented! Our enemies perſecution was not worſe then our friends impatience; nor the deſpight of the one, then the deſpair of the other. Oh our ſlavery hath thus long continued, we are a loſt people, <hi>This is of the Lord, why ſhould we wait upon the Lord any longer?</hi> 2 Kings 6.33. What do our Stateſ-men comfort us? do our pulpits bid us hope for better times? both of us ſeemed but as Impoſtours to them; Sure I am, for our ſelves, that if we preached unto them, that upon true repentance they might yet expect a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption out of all miſeries, they were ready to deride us, and defy us, and to count us ſeditious, yea to call us Temple-Lunaticks, and infatuated, and intoxicated Royaliſts. But hath not God ſhamed this incredulous generation? yes, and taught them confidence in the midſt of exigents. Aſſiance is the beſt Diet-bread to live upon in tribulation.</p>
            <q>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note place="margin">Euripid.</note>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Hopes feeds the exiled.</hi> Whatſoever ſad Prognoſticks there be for the preſent, yet</p>
            <q>Coelum adhuc volvitur,<note place="margin">Theocrit.</note>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Heaven is yet turning about.</hi> The Poles ſtand not more firmely, then Gods decrees; the acceſſe of the Sun to the Tropicks is not more certain, then the motion of Gods unchangeable purpoſes. Can God for ever forſake the true members of the Church? no <hi>Hell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gates ſhall not prevail against them. This is unto me as the waters of Noah.</hi> Iſ. 54.9. <hi>The promiſes of God are yea, and Amen.</hi> That which is not now apparent may afterwards be manifeſted, that which is not now ſeen may in a ſhort time be ſeen, <hi>Thine eyes ſhall ſee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fifthly, this doth ſhew the high joy that there ought to be upon the enjoyment of a ſight. Was it but ſaid, <hi>Thine eyes ſhall ſee,</hi> and do thine eyes ſee? then where are thine eyes? haſt thou the deſire of thy eyes, and is there not the delight of thine eyes? oh yes, <hi>the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:100932:11"/>light of the eyes rejoyceth the heart.</hi> Prov. 15.30. For wherefore hath God made the ſeeing eye, but that when it doth ſee, what it would ſee, it ſhould ſee it with a tranſportment? then the eyes ſhould be lift up to Heaven, and they ſhould look upon the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour with an exultation; then there ſhould be the magnifying tongue for the ſeeing eye, and a thankfull heart for the joyfull ſight; then there ſhould be praiſe for the fruit of Divine Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and bleſſing for a bleſſing. For does God viſit us, and are we not ſenſible of his preſence? does he put an Object to our eyes, and know we not what it is to be Eye-witneſſes of his goodneſſe, and kindneſſe? what ſtupid Spectatours are we? how blind are our eyes? then we deſerve not ſuch a preſent, nor to have ſeen ſuch a mercy. Contempt, penury, thraldome had been fitter for us to have looked upon, then peace, ſafety, proſperity. <hi>Do ye thus requite the Lord oh fooliſh people?</hi> thus, for breaking your yoake, ridding you from hard bondage, and ſetting your feet in a large place? Hath he filled your land with ſongs, and can ye not hear? hath he repleniſhed the Nation with aſtoniſhable ſights, and can ye not ſee? Is this your entertainment of bleſſings? is this your glee upon mercies? I find more ſparkles, and glowing incentives then theſe in the breſts of Heathens; the Aeginets when they returned from Troy, their kindred which never thought to have ſeen them again (ſo many of their fellows being deſtroyed, with the wars,<note place="margin">Plut. Graecan. quaeſt.</note> and tempeſts) o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened their doors to them, and well-comed them home with ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne Feaſts, and ſacrificed ſixteen dayes to Neptune with dances. The Grecians which had been a long time in the wars of <hi>Cyrus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diod. l. <hi>14.</hi> Biblioth.</note> when they had liberty to return home to their own Country, they no ſooner came to the ſight of the Euxine Sea, but they ſhouted as if they would have ſhaken down the woods. <hi>Flaminius</hi> by the ſound of Trumpet proclaiming liberty to the Corinthians,<note place="margin">Plut. in Flamin.</note> Euboians Phocenſes, Locrenſes, Achaians, and the greateſt part of Greece, when they expected nothing but bondage, their acclamations were ſo loud that they were heard from the Iſthmian games to the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhore; and have we neither heart-ſtrings, nor tongue-ſtrings to make melody upon ſuch occaſions? where then is our grace? where is our zeal? know we not what it is to come out of a Correction-houſe? know we not what it is to lay aſide fetters? oh that God ſhould deliver ſuch a people, as underſtand not the worth of liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty!
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:100932:12"/>or bleſſe ſuch a people as have not eyes to ſee the bleſſing! what? ſenſeleſſe in what we do feel? and blind in what we do ſee? can there be more flinty hearts? and atrofied eyes? But thus it is, we are ſick for many things when we want them, and ſurfeted when we do enjoy them; we would give millions for them when they are abſent, but ſcarcely a gale of praiſes for them, when they are preſent; as ſweet things periſh with the taſt, ſo happy things with the ſight; we look on them once, and never caſt an eye to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them after. We are much the better for Gods favours, but what is he the better for our intereſt in them? Who would think, that this were the Land, where God had ſhot out his arrow of deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance, brought people out of horrible ſlavery, broken the ſtaff of the wicked, hath given the anſwer of peace, commanded the bloudy ſword into the ſcabbard, raiſed up a hill of bleſſings, lighted up his candle, made a waſt ground to flouriſh again as the roſe? What ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour hath God for all theſe large mercies? what but a few ſmiles and frolicks, rantings and chantings, feaſtings and plumings, a little good language, and a little good ſtudying of old principles? are there fewer riots, oathes, bribes, frauds in the Nation then for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly? what conſciences are renewed, or hearts changed by the ſenſe of all theſe bleſſings? what? are the Church, or the Univerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or the captives, or the poor the better for the change of the times? Do every one now emulate who ſhall be the nobler Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factour? or excell moſt in pious works? where are the Characters of our thankfulneſſe? or the monuments that we have raiſed up to Gods bleſſings? Are there many of theſe hallowed portions offered up to Heaven? are there many of theſe religious Dedications? no, I am afraid that in ſtead of the fruit of the Bleſſing, there is nothing but the benefit and advantage of it minded, to lay hold on rich offices, and to fall to trading with a kind of eagerneſſe, and to build Banquetting-houſes for Libertines to recreate themſelves together; but there is not a trowel yet provided for God, nor a Carver ſpoken to ſet up a graven piece to Heaven. Where then is our eying of Gods bleſſing? no, we did ſee it, but we did but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire a glance of it, we have viewed it enough, we are weary with looking on it. But if we be no better Obſervers of Objects, is there not a defect in our eye-ſight? yes, there is either a diſtemper in the Conjunctive of the eye, or ſome tubercle in our eye-lid, or ſome
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:100932:12"/>obſtruction in the prunal, there is either a <hi>phthiſis,</hi> or <hi>Strabiſmus,</hi> or <hi>Hippos,</hi> whereby an <hi>Ophthalmy, Aegilops, Pisthia, Mydriaſis,</hi> or <hi>Cataract</hi> is gotten into the eye, for we cannot ſee what we did ſee, we cannot ſee, what is yet plainly to be ſeen. Oh therefore let us betake our ſelves to ſome good Oculiſt, that we may recover our ſight, for it is a ſhame to be ſo bad-ſighted in diſcerning bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings. There are many which maligne us this happineſſe, their eyes rowle to the corners that they might not look upon it, there is this <hi>Oculus nequam</hi> in the head of every Sectary, or Phanatick; now though there be <hi>lithiaſis,</hi> or <hi>epiphora</hi> in our Adverſaries, ſo that they ſeem like goggle-eyed, or ſquint-eyed perſons looking with a diſtortion upon our proſperous condition, yet ſhall there be <hi>em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſma,</hi> or <hi>myopia</hi> in us that we ſhould be dark-eyed, or narrow-eyed in ſeeing our own felicity? no, that which we deſired to ſee with ſo much vehemence, let us now look upon it intenſively; oh let us embrace that <hi>Rachel</hi> with all manner of affection, for which we endured ſo many years of hardſhip to obtain her. Oh that our God went at a great price with us, that we would weigh him out a National gratitude according to the value of his favours, that our apprehenſion were as ſignal as his goodneſs! We can never Arithme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically requite him, let us give him ſome Geometrical proportion. Let us conſpire together to ſend him a bountifull preſent, yea ſay, here Lord take a freewill-offering for the benefit of our liberties, lives, conſciences. Thou haſt given us a Kingdom-redemption, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of a Kingdom-retribution. Oh that we knew how to retaliate! to weigh out God a recompenſe according to the ſhekel of the Sanctuary! that every one of us would ſtrive who ſhould have the moſt devout heart, or the moſt thankfull hand. Will we be ſparing to ſuch a munificent God? can there ever be enough given for ſuch Halcyon-dayes? What have ye gained by them? ſhall God riſe up a looſer? no, let the extenſion of our commemoration, and remunera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion anſwer the latitude of Gods benevolence and benediction. <hi>It becometh well the just to be thankfull,</hi> then what degree of thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe do we owe to God Almighty? ye that are ſtrict in your engagements, and deſire to ſatisfy every man to a Deneere, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber your obligation to Heaven, and pay God his debt, his preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion-debt. The felicity of the Nation is manifeſt, the piety of the Nation is tried; We are the happyeſt people upon earth, let us be
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:100932:13"/>the holyeſt people upon earth; whereſoever God hath his ſpiritual race, let the Engliſh-man be the Saint; Let every one of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Church, be a transformed Proteſtant. It is a ſhame, that here ſhould be a Libertine, or that any Sectary, or Papiſt ſhould excell us in purity. Gods mercies require more innocency at our hands, the brightneſſe of his favours oblige us to brightneſſe of ſanctity, yea that the Kingdom all over ſhould ſhine in the radian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of grace. Oh therefore let us enamel our bleſſings, and as we have reigning mercies amongſt us, ſo let us ſet a Crown upon the head of them. Let here be the new creatures, the children of light, the lively ſtones, the ſeed of the bleſſed, the trees of righteouſneſſe, the people that are partakers of the divine nature, that have a lot amongſt them which are ſanctified, that are bought from men, men that this world is not worthy of, yea let the whole Land be turned into a Kingdom of Prieſts. We ought to do this for our very ſights ſake, our Objects do require us to be ſuch Ornaments, and our mercies ſuch Mirrours. What ſhould be ſeen in us, when ſo much is ſeen by us? We ſee that which we did not ſee, we ſee that, which we were once afraid we ſhould never have ſeen; Though we be now in fruition, and our eyes do ſee, yet let us remember how remote this happineſſe was, at what a diſtance the Object was placed from us, we had it but in expectation, or our greateſt propinquity to it was in a promiſe, the ſight reſerved to the future, <hi>Thine eyes ſhall ſee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 Part. <hi>The King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have done with the opening of the Cabinet, I now come to take out the Gemme. Seeing there is a ſight I would fain ſee what it is; Is it the beſt of the Nation? then I wipe mine eyes to look upon him. Hath he been hid in a cloud? then it will be pleaſure to ſee him, when God does preſent him. Hath he not for many years been ſeen, and is now the ſeeing time come? then I can no longer with-hold mine eyes from him, no I paſſionately deſire to ſee the King. <hi>Thine eyes ſhall ſee the King. The King.</hi> From hence ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, that <hi>A King is the perfection of all earthly Objects.</hi> Of all deſireable and delectable <hi>Sights</hi> that this world can afford, <hi>a King is the ſplendour of them. Thine eyes ſhall ſee the King.</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:100932:13"/>He is <hi>publici decoris lampas, the lamp of publick brightneſſe;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Caſsiod. Seneca in Hecuba. Matthias Agrit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius. Lud. Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves ad Henr. <hi>8.</hi> Homer. Greg. in Paſtorali. Agap. diae. de off. reg. Philo Iud. de Charit. Aug. de <hi>12.</hi> abuſ. grad. <hi>6.</hi> Procop. in Geneſ. <hi>2.</hi> Naz. Tertull. Chryſoſt.</note> 
               <hi>Coeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum egregius labor, the Maſter-piece of the divine Artiſan; Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubitor communis ſalutis,</hi> The Watch-man, or Sentinel of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſafety; <hi>magnum regni columen,</hi> the great pillar of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the heavenly dew to water a Nation; <hi>Caput quod ab alto providet,</hi> The head which from above doth provide for multitudes; <hi>Oculus innatus corpori,</hi> the eye ſet in the head to look for the general good; <hi>Peritus Gubernator,</hi> the skilfull Marriner which doth preſerve the whole bark from periſhing; <hi>Paxillus reipu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blicae,</hi> the ſtay, or ſupporter, upon which hang the weight of a whole Commonwealth; <hi>Ignis qui urit, &amp; lucem praebet,</hi> The fire which doth burn up all the wicked, and doth give light to all the Godly. Yea, the Ancients knowing the high benefit of ſuch a ſupreme Governour know not how to beſtow Elogies, and Encomiaſticks enough up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him; And doth not Scripture concur with theſe, and ſet out a King with as great luſtre? yes, <hi>I have ſaid ye are Gods,</hi> Pſ. 82.6. As if a King were <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Medal, wherein Gods own Image is repreſented, <hi>Alter Deus in terris,</hi> another God upon earth. For (me think) I ſee in a King a ſemblance of Gods infinite being, his quickening ſpirit, his out-ſtretched arm, and his glorious Majeſty. He is not the Divinity, but a Synopſis of the Divinity, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a God exemplified, or effigiated. Why are Kings ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to <hi>Abraham, Kings ſhall come out of thy loines,</hi> and ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied of by <hi>Jacob, Judah ſhall have a Scepter,</hi> and ſo paſſionate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſired by the people, <hi>Give us a King,</hi> and ſo confirmed by God Almighty, by an Inſtitution, an Oath, and by the holy oyle, yea, why is God himſelf called <hi>the great King, the King of glory, and the King of Kings,</hi> if there were any thing upon earth more emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent then a King? As it is the greateſt curſe upon earth to want a King; For <hi>many dayes ſhall paſſe in Iſrael without a King.</hi> Hoſ. 3.4. and <hi>becauſe we feared not the Lord, therefore we have no King.</hi> Hoſ. 10.3. So it is the greateſt bleſſing to have a King, for <hi>the ſhout of a King is amongst them.</hi> Num. 23.21. and <hi>the Lord hath given you a King.</hi> 1 Sam. 12.13. and, <hi>Why dost thou cry out? Is there not a King in thee?</hi> Micah 4.9. as if a King were there, all were well. When I read of ſo much reverence, &amp; awfull ſubjection enjoyned to Kings, that we muſt <hi>ſubmit to them for the Lords ſake,</hi> and not <hi>reſist them for fear of damnation,</hi> that we muſt not
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:100932:14"/>
               <hi>provoke them to wrath,</hi> not <hi>ſtand in an evil thing against them, not curſe them in our bed-chambers;</hi> how do I think that Kings are priceleſſely tendered by God Almighty, and that they are his chief Favourites! yea, wherefore does he command ſo many prayers and ſupplications to be made for them, and that with a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>eſpecially,</hi> as if he would have the lips of a whole Nation to ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice for their ſafety and welfare, if Kings were not the principal perſons, which God had under his protection, and tutelage? Well then if either Gods love, or his lawes, his titles, or his priviledges, his miſſion, or commiſſion, his conſecration, or conſervation, his impreſſe, or his Image, his watchfull providence, or his irefull ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance concerning Kings be to be regarded, we cannot imagine any perſons more conſpicuous or precious, excellent or eminent then Kings. No, mans eyes can ſee no more exquiſite, and magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Creature upon earth then a <hi>King,</hi> for <hi>Thine eyes ſhall ſee the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. This ſerves firſt to ſhew us <hi>the high ſins of this Nation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Applic.</note> 
               <hi>which for many years deprived us of this happy ſight.</hi> Did we not <hi>provoke the eyes of Gods glory?</hi> yes, we may diſcern it by the judgement upon our eyes, We ſaw not a King. God is deeply incenſed, when he <hi>doth take away the Diademe.</hi> Ezech. 21.26. and people have been Tranſgreſſours to purpoſe, when it may be ſaid to them, <hi>Where is thy King that ſhould help thee in all thy Cities?</hi> Hoſ. 13.10. yea, when <hi>the Crown is fallen from their head, they may cry wo unto us we have ſinned.</hi> Lament. 5.16. Have they not broken Gods Lawes grievouſly, when <hi>the breakor ſhall come up before them, and lay hold upon him that ſitteth in the Throne, ſo that the King ſhall go out before them, and the Lord ſhall be upon their heads?</hi> Micah. 2.13. oh God is ready <hi>to diſannull the Covenant, which he made with his people, when he doth break this ſtaffe of Beauty.</hi> Zach. 11.10. would to God then, that we were as ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of our Sins as our Sufferings, and our wickedneſſe, as our wretchedneſſe. We loſt the ſight of a King for our guilty eyes, and have we not gained the ſight of him again with the ſome crimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal eyes? have we ſo minded and mortified, revieved and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced our known corruptions, that we welcomed the <hi>King</hi> into a cleanſed Land? were there none but Penitents, which fetched him in? It is true, that though there be <hi>corruption in the wound,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:100932:14"/>yet there is health in the medicine,</hi> but do not we carry our old ulcers about us, inſomuch that though we have been wounded,<note place="margin">In vulne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſamies in medici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio.</note> yet we refuſe to apply a plaiſter for cure, ſo that our former botches remaining, we have but brought home the King to a Lazer houſe? Oh that we had had as much deſire to renew our conſciences, as to renew our State, and to take away the cords of our iniquity,<note place="margin">Chryſ. de pun. ſ. <hi>3.</hi> Nos, qui vulnera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti ſumus, obligari poeniten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia eru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beſcimur. Bern. Serm. de circumciſ.</note> as to take off our fetters, and to ſee the face of Chriſt, as to ſee the face of the King; but I doubt, that there have been few of theſe deſires, or few of theſe eyes; we had eyes to look onely to our deliverance, not to our duties, to the change of our miſeries, not of our manners,<note place="margin">n="*" Laert. l. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Lyc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> the ſcholar of <hi>Straton</hi> could ſpeak ſo eloquently that he was called <hi>Glycon,</hi> ſweet ſpeech, but he wrot ſo harſhly, that no man would read what he penned; So we are curious Rhetoricians to ſpeak of good things, but the worſt Scribes in the world to write out accurately in our converſations, what we have delivered ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantly with our tongues. What we were at the beginning of our miſeries the ſame we are ſtill, and have gotten no more mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by paſſing through variety of calamities, then fiſhes do get in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them any ſalt taſt by ſwimming a long time in brackiſh Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waters,<note place="margin">Apollon. de Hiſt. mirabil.</note> or then <hi>Eunomus</hi> did get any purging from his corrupt hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, by taking two and twenty potions of Hollebore. Oh inflexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble hearts oh fruitleſſe judgements! It were well therefore, that we would diſperſe that cloud that kept the light of the Sun ſo long from us; do we ſuffer theſe thieves to range up, and down at liberty, till they have robbed us once more of our Gemme? This had need to be the contrite Land, when our impenitency hath done us ſo much miſchief. Oh let us know the treſpaſſe by the puniſhment; our ſins ſtript us of much honour, and left the Land naked, when they plucked the Robe of Majeſty from the back of it. Let us know at laſt that our Sins are old Chaſers, when they drove a King out of the Land, it is a judgement to be deprived of a King, when it is an happineſſe <hi>to ſee a King. Thine eyes ſhall ſee the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, this doth ſhew that <hi>the want of a King is the Iulet of all infelicity.</hi> For how can that Land be happy, where <hi>the eyes do not ſee a King?</hi> no, <hi>then ſervants ride on horſeback.</hi> 10. Eccleſ. 7. <hi>The people ſhall be oppreſſed every one of another, and every one of his neighbour, the children ſhall preſume against the ancient, and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:100932:15"/>the vile against the honourable.</hi> Iſ. 3.5. for when <hi>the Kings are fallen,</hi> Hoſ. 7.7. all welfare fall with them, then preſently <hi>they are mixt with ſtrange worſhips, ſtrangers devour their ſtrength, &amp; gray hairs are here and there upon them,</hi> Hoſ. 7.8.9. yea, <hi>when Princes are hanged up by the hand, then the young are taken to grind, and the children fall under the wood, the Elders ceaſe from the gate, and the young men from their ſongs, the joy of their heart is gone, and their dance is turned into mourning.</hi> Lament. 5.12, 13, 14, 15. nay God doth no ſooner <hi>remove the Crown, but the Kingdome is no more the ſame it was, then preſently God overturn, overturn, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verturn.</hi> Ezech. 21.26.27. when the true Shepherd is removed, then there is nothing to be ſeen in the Nation, but <hi>the instruments of a fooliſh Shepheard,</hi> of ſuch a Shepheard, which will not <hi>look for the thing that is lost, nor ſeek the tender Lambs, nor heal that which is hurt, nor feed that which ſtandeth up, but he ſhall eat the fleſh of the fat, and tear their clawes in pieces.</hi> Zach. 11.15.16. Take away ſuch a Shepheard, and the poor flock goeth to woefull deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, for <hi>Ariſe oh Sword upon my Shepheard, and upon the man that is my fellow,</hi> that is, Gods immediate Vicegerent, and what then? <hi>and the ſheep are ſcattered, and God turn his hand upon the little ones, And in all the Land ſaith the Lord two parts therein ſhall be cut off, and dye.</hi> Zach. 13.7.8. So that where a King is want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, what but diſorder, diſtraction, devaſtation, and deſolation is to be expected? And have not we had experience of it? yes, ſo ſoon as a King was gone, how did every one wear the Crown, and ſit in the Chair of State? peaſants were Princes, and Mechanicks Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs, never ſuch a ſpawne of new Lords, nor a litter of upſtart Rulers ſeen, paradoxes were principles, and Sanctity was little bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then South-ſaying, the Temple was a kind of Tiring-room, liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty was leaguing, free trade was purchaſing Delinquents Eſtates, and allegiance was conſpiracy. Were there ever ſo many fundamental Lawes overthrown, ſo many families ruined, ſo many millions ſpent, ſo many bowels torn out in five hundred years within this Realm, as there were in this ſhort ſpace of King-routing? alas conſciences, eſtates, priviledges, ſpeeches, looks, affections, labours, lawes, lives were all ſubject to the will of the inſulting Conquerour. So that as <hi>Pyrrhus</hi> ſaid of <hi>Sicily</hi> in reſpect of the Romans,<note place="margin">Sabell. l. <hi>9.</hi> E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> and Carthagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians, ſo might it be ſaid of this Land in reſpect of our factious
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:100932:15"/>Rulers, it was but the <hi>Stage where mad men plaid their prizes;</hi> and as <hi>Ate</hi> is ſaid to be cauſe of all the labours of <hi>Hercules,</hi> ſo our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting a King was the Original of all the miſeries of the Nation. <hi>In thoſe dayes when there was no King in Iſrael, every man did that, which was good in his own eyes.</hi> Judg. 17.6. and we found it, for humour was then order, power was law, and divination was the Divinity of the times. The Fox-burrow of Triers took away mens gifts, the Cutpurſe-hall of a Committee of Indemnity took away mens rights, and the bloudy Shambles of an High Court of Juſtice took away mens heads. Oh ſad age of arbitrary commands! oh diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Reigne! oh miſerable Realm without a King! will ye ever engage again to be ruled without King, or Houſe of Lords? will ye ever be ready to take an oath of Abjuration again againſt a ſingle Perſon? Then be ye for my part ſingle, and ſingular, deſperate, and wilfull Bondmen. For it is to make the whole Nation a ſlave to be deſtitute of a King, the preſence of a King being the preſervation of a Kingdome, for <hi>Thine eyes ſhall ſee the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, this doth ſerve to exhort us to be chearfull Seers. For have ye got a King again to look upon?</p>
            <q>
               <note place="margin">Virg.</note> — viſum mirabile Cunctis.</q>
            <p>It is a ſight that the eyes of a whole Nation might behold with ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration. Do ye not bleſſe your eyes then, that ye are ſeeing that, which ye have been ſo long ſeeking for? Do ye not know what ye could not ſee, what ye would have ſeen, what ye do ſee? Do the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light of a Kingdom grieve you? doth <hi>the deſire of your eyes</hi> offend you? Have ye not what can be ſeen? can ye ſee a better? <hi>If thine eye then offend thee pluck it out,</hi> pluck out that evil glaucome out of thine eye. <hi>The eye is the light of the body.</hi> Have as clear an eye, as can be to ſee ſo bright an Object. Is there a diſeaſed eye here? oh cure the malady. Are there any moles here? away with ſuch Blinkards; are there any Bats here? away with ſuch unlucky birds; Did the ſight of Oſtriches offend you, and ſhall not the ſigh: of a <hi>Phoenix</hi> pleaſe you?<note place="margin">Quivis delectatur cum lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deat. Demoſth. Ficinus.</note> 
               <hi>Every man is delighted when he doth ſee the light,</hi> and what is a King, but the <hi>Light of our eyes? The eye doth receive the beams of the Sun in a ſpiritual manner,</hi> &amp; ſo do ye the ſight of a King, that glorious Sun. Was <hi>Jacob</hi> ſo delighted when he heard that his Son <hi>Joſeph</hi> was alive, that <hi>his heart failed him,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:100932:16"/>and his ſpirit revived?</hi> Gen. 25.27.28. Were the Iſraelites ſo af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected when they heard that the Arke (which had a long time been kept captive amongſt the Philiſtines) was returning, that they left their wheat-harveſt to look upon the Arke? 1. Sam. 6.13. were the Jewes in <hi>Shuſhan</hi> ſo tranſported that <hi>Hamans</hi> bloudy decree was reverſed, that it cauſed <hi>joy and gladneſſe amongst them, and they kept a Feast, and a good day?</hi> 9. Eſter 22. then what great me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lody and feſtivity may it be to us that we have our <hi>Joſeph</hi> to look upon, our Arke gilded within and without to behold, and a day of <hi>Purim</hi> to keep for a deliverance from the ſavageſt decree, that the malice of man could invent? Oh that we have opportunity to commemorate theſe things, that we have the happineſs with our eyes freely to ſee them! was it a joyfull thing once to hear of a King, and ſhall it not be much more joyfull to <hi>ſee a King?</hi> yes, <hi>the ſenſe of ſight is much more perfect then that of hearing.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Senſus vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctior eſt auditu. Plotinus.</note> If your eyes then ſhould not take pleaſure in that which was once ſo comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to your eares, your eyes are wonderfully diſtant from your eares, as <hi>Thales</hi> ſaid. Oh then that all the hearts of the Kingdome ſhould not ſpring with joy, that all the feet of the Kingdom ſhould not leap with Triumph, that all the eyes of the Kingdom ſhould not gaze with pleaſure to ſee ſuch a ſolacing, ſatisfying, triumphant Object preſented to the ſight! Ye have not now a King living, or honoured beyond Sea, or counted worthy of a Crown by very ſtrangers which converſed with him, but the faces of his own peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are bleſſed with the ſight of him; he is come towards you, he is come near you, he is come home to you. And <hi>what went ye out to ſee?</hi> nay what is brought into your Throne to ſee? Can there be a more bright, amiable, delectable, ſplendid, illuſtrious, ſupereminent, matchleſſe, majeſtical ſight for the eyes of a whole Realm to look upon then a <hi>King?</hi> no, <hi>Thine eyes ſhall ſee the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, this ſerves to exhort all <hi>to make a King Royal.</hi> And how Royal? but in being your ſelves Loyal? How is he a King with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Royalty? and how are ye Subjects without Loyalty? The He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes have a Proverb; <hi>that a man ſhould fly out of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, where a King is not obeyed.</hi> And doubtleſſe no Nation ſhaken with a Quag-mire, or toſſed with an Earth-quake is more dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to ſtand upon. Rebellions are the burning feavers of Realmes, the Deluges of States, the Eclipſes of Nations, the Hericanoes
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:100932:16"/>of Kingdomes. <hi>Rebellion is as the ſin of Witchcraft,</hi> Sam. 15.23. for then all the Magicians are at work, and uſing all the preſtigiatory inventions of their black Art. <hi>Simon Magus, Balaam, Jannes</hi> and <hi>Jambres</hi> had not more pernicious rules, and practiſes, then theſe State-witches, they are like the <hi>Bythiae</hi> in <hi>Scythia,</hi> which had four apples of the eye in their heads,<note place="margin">Plin. l. <hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> and killed all which they looked upon with their angry eyes. Traitours upon earth are but the diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of <hi>Judas,</hi> or the State-ſtudents of <hi>Achitophel,</hi> or the Spirits that learn their aſpiring Art of Lucifer. Goodly pedagogues that they are trained under, if I would have an Academy of Hell ſet up, I would have Traytours there commence, and become Graduates. The Law taught no ſuch principles. No, <hi>The Fathers children muſt bow down before him that is in chief authority.</hi> Gen. 49.8. <hi>Who can lay his hand upon the Lords anointed, and be guiltleſſe?</hi> 1. Sam. 26.9. and <hi>against a King there is no riſing up.</hi> Prov. 30.31. The Goſpel hath no ſuch Maximes. No, <hi>let every ſoul be ſubject to the higher powers, for there is no power, but of God, and the powers that be are ordained of God. Whoſoever therefore reſiſteth the power reſiſteth the Ordinance of God, and they which reſist ſhall receive to themſelves damnation.</hi> Rom. 13.1.2. <hi>Put them in remembrance that they be ſubject to principalities, and powers, and that they be obedient.</hi> Tit. 3.1. <hi>Submit your ſelves unto every Ordinance of man for the Lords ſake, whether it be to the King as Supreme.</hi> 1 Pet. 2.13. <hi>Woe be to them, that walk in the gain-ſaying of Corah.</hi> Jude 11. Seditions are <hi>works of the fleſh.</hi> Gal. 5.20. Deſpiſers of Government, and thoſe which <hi>ſpeak evil of dignities are called Drea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers, which defile the fleſh.</hi> Jude 8. <hi>Traytours, heady high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded men</hi> are put amongſt the wickedeſt people of the moſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillous times. 2. Tim. 3.4. Oh then that men live under a King fomenting ſedition, gendring treaſon, yea that count it a part of their Divinity to caſt firebrands, and fire Beacons, and ſtrike up drums, and diſplay colours, and ſhoot off warning pieces againſt their Soveraigns, that if they have not a plyable King, they will fright him into Accommodation, if they have not a King accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their own mind, they will fight him into their bent, this is Pole-axe-religion, Gunpowder-Divinity. How can theſe profeſſe the name of God? take a Bible into their hands? preach the Goſpel of peace? be ghoſtly Fathers at the hour of diſſolution? or prepare
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:100932:17"/>men for Gods judgement ſeat? They which ſhould teach all the Land obedience, do they teach nothing but mutinies, inſurrections, tumults, factions, defections, conſpiracy, diſloyalty? <hi>Thou which ſayest thou knowest Gods will, and allowest of the things that are excellent, and perſwadeſt thy ſelf, that thou art a guide of the blind, and a light to them that are in darkneſſe, an inſtructer of them that lack diſcretion, a teacher of the unlearned, which hast the form of knowledge, and of the truth in the Law. Thou which teacheſt another, teacheſt thou not thy ſelf?</hi> Rom. 2.18, 19, 20, 21. If thou thy ſelf beeſt a Wolf, how wilt thou get Lambs? Chriſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſent his Meſſengers to be Muſter-maſters, or Maſter-Gunners. A Preacher of all others ſhould be the great Phyſician, Breach-cloſer, Peace-maker upon earth; Chriſts patience, the Martyrs aſhes, the counſel of peace in his lips, and the bleſſed Sacraments in his hands ſhould teach him this. As he is a Watch-man he ſhould not be a Match-man, as he is a Maſter-builder, he ſhould not be a Maſter-pioner, as he is an Angel of the Churches, he ſhould not be an Angel of the bottomleſſe pit. Is rebellion any of the ſincere milk which ſhould be ſucked out of his breſts? any of the pure oyle which ſhould burn in his lamp? any of the fat things, and fined things at his ſumptuous Feaſt? any of the fragrant ſmels amongſt his ſweet odours? Is this for Chriſt to be the Star, the Vine, the Shepheard, to ride upon a white Horſe, and to hold the four winds in his hand? Is this for Chriſt to eat butter, and hony, not to cry, nor cauſe his voice to be heard in the ſtreets, to weare a ſeame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe coat, and to be led dumb before the ſhearers? where is Chriſts innocency, meekneſſe, his rebuking his Diſciples for calling for fire from Heaven, his commanding St. <hi>Peter</hi> to put up his ſword in any of theſe things? If <hi>the weapons of our warfare be not carnal,</hi> 2 Cor. 10.4. then why are ſpiritual men ſo active in a carnal war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare? theſe may propheſy in Chriſts name, but it is to be doubted whether they ſhall not be turned off with a <hi>Neſcio vos,</hi> I know you not. In it is vain to talk of the profound myſteries of Chriſt, when theſe depths of Sathan are amongſt them. All the drugs in their ſhop are ſuſpected by this one box of Aconite. Theſe may have Chriſts Croſſe often in their mouths, but did they ever lay it upon their ſhoulders? they may have drunk of his new wine, but can they drink his ſpunge full of vinegar? they may hold his keyes
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:100932:17"/>in their hands, but can they endure to put his yoak about their necks? they have preached things upon the houſe-top, but can they put their mouths in the duſt? they can ſhew their confident faces to Congregations, but can they give their backs to the ſmiters, and their cheeks to the nippers, and not hide their faces from ſhame and ſpitting? no, they may be men of very great parts, but I doubt not of very great patience. God is ſo tender of the peace of the Church, that he doth <hi>charge the daughters of Jeruſalem by the roes, and hinds, that they ſtirre not up, nor waken his love untill ſhe pleaſe.</hi> Cantic. 3.5. but pleaſe, or not pleaſe upon the leaſt diſcontent they care not to waken and fright her too; if ſhe will not awake of her ſelf they will blow trumpets in her ears, and make her open her eyes with a peale of Ordnance. So that they ſeem not to be Preachers of pacification, but Lecturers, under the ſlag of defiance, and Chaplains of the Gun-roome. Now what ſanctity can there be, where there is ſedition? what conſcience where there is conſpiracy? they which care not to violate a manifeſt precept, what lawes of God can they be thought truly to dread? this is a ſin ſo odious that the very Heathens have abhorred it. When the<note place="margin">n="*" Quomodo convenit, Oh Ephori tot juve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ei cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere, qui ſuam ipſius pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triam prodidit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Plut. in Lacon. Iſta ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nu non proditu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus es a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam civi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſ. l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi> Plut. Herod. l. <hi>6.</hi> Suidas. Diod. l. <hi>19.</hi> Alex. ab. Alex. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>13.</hi> Pauſaniay in Phoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis.</note> 
               <hi>Ephori</hi> would have committed the ſtrength of their Country into the hands of a rebellious Leader, ſaith <hi>Agis, Why do ye truſt him with any thing; who hath betrayed his own Country?</hi> When <hi>Cili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con</hi> had betrayed the <hi>Priennenſes</hi> as he ſtretched to receive his meat, <hi>Theagenes</hi> cut off his hand, ſaying, <hi>thou ſhalt not have a right hand to betray another City.</hi> When <hi>Archidamus</hi> would have inticed <hi>Nicostratus</hi> to betray his Country, oh ſaith he, <hi>boast no more of thy high pedigree, for thou ſeemeſt not to be of the ſtock of Hercules, becauſe thou dost tempt me to ſo baſe a thing.</hi> How ſharply did <hi>Artaphernes</hi> reprove <hi>Hiſtiaeus</hi> for making the ſhoe of rebellion for the Ionians, that <hi>Ariſtagoras</hi> might put it on. <hi>Xerxes</hi> becauſe <hi>Aribarzanes</hi> rebelled againſt him, he took him, &amp; crucified him. <hi>Apollonides</hi> becauſe the <hi>Stymphalians</hi> rebelled againſt <hi>Caſſander,</hi> he ſubduing them burnt them all to aſhes. <hi>Aemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> after he had conquered <hi>Perſeus</hi> taking many Romans which had been Rebels againſt their own Country, he cauſed them to be trampled to death by Elephants. The <hi>Amphyctions</hi> after the battel with <hi>Xerxes</hi> taking the <hi>Phocenſes</hi> who had ſided with the enemy againſt the Crecians, and robbed the Temple of <hi>Apollo,</hi> they ſlew
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:100932:18"/>many of them, raſed three of their prime Cities, cauſing them to dwell afterwards in villages, &amp; laid a taxe of threeſcore talents year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for the repairing the Temple. Oh then that that ſin which hath been held a horrid crime amongſt Heathens ſhould be accounted a prime virtue amongſt Chriſtians! is it not a ſhame that the light of Nature ſhould ſhine brightlier then the light of the Goſpel? is it not a ſcandal that God ſhould provoke ſuch Profeſſours to jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy by a fooliſh Nation? Shall Gentiles teach Chriſtians Divinity? how will theſe juſtify their ſelves at the laſt day, when the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens ſhall riſe up in judgement againſt them? If ye are then to look upon a King, as a King, beware of <hi>Salomons winking eye.</hi> When ye have not faithful eyes to look upon a King,<note place="margin">Chryſ. hom. <hi>55.</hi> in Iohan.</note> ye will ſoon have treacherous feet, yea <hi>amiſſis oculis fruſtra ſunt pedes,</hi> if your eyes have loſt their reverence to a King, your feet will ſoon have loſt their obedience to him. I truſt our King hath none about him, which are troubled in their eye-ſight, if he ſhould, then thoſe which have bad eyes, will ſoon have bad hearts. I wiſh them all to have good optick nerves, good Cryſtalline humours, good viſory ſpirits. Pity it is, that there ſhould be any vermine at Court, any ſpiders hanging upon the Kings rafters, that there ſhould be any bad tongues nigh to the Kings eares, any bad eyes nigh to the Kings face; no, though there may be ſome diſtempered ſights in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, yet it were ſhame and horrour, if there ſhould be a <hi>Poly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemus,</hi> and a <hi>Cyclops,</hi> howſoever a <hi>Tireſias</hi> and a <hi>Hypſea.</hi> What they which eat the Kings bread, and are ſworne to preſerve the Kings perſon, not clear-ſighted to ſee his honour? then they deſerve neither the eyes in their heads, nor the necks on their ſhoulders. The <hi>Furcifer</hi> is the fitteſt <hi>Oculiſt</hi> to cure ſuch bloud-ſhotten eyes. And as I would take all bad eyes out of the Court, ſo my deſire is to free the Kingdome from ſuch bad-ſighted people. Rebellion is an high defect in the eye of Subjection, therefore let all beware how they comply with the ſand-blind, ſtark-blind generation, for <hi>If the blind lead the blind both will fall into the ditch.</hi> Therefore if there be a King, then amongſt you give him the reverence and right of his Name, that is, be ye Loyal to him. Do ye all then <hi>make a Covenant with your eyes not to look upon a maid,</hi> that beautifull Damoſel of diſloyalty; if ſhe with her fair ſpeech can make you to yield, and with her flattering lips intice you to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:100932:18"/>ſtep in to her, ye go like an oxe to the ſlaughter, and like a fool to the ſtocks of correction, till a dart doth ſtrike through your liver, or ye be as a bird, which haſteneth to the ſnare, not knowing that it is for your life. Beware therefore that ye do not commit for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication with that noted proſtitute, ſhe will bring you to a morſel of bread, and hunt for your precious life; howſoever a wound, and diſhonour ye ſhall get, and your reproach ſhall never be wiped away. Keep therefore a chaſt heart to your own Bridegroom, and ſeek not after ſtrange fleſh. If ye do commit uncleanneſſe, ye may thank your wandring eyes, and your eyes full of adultery, Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy is that Government, which ye ought to be eſpouſed to. Look therefore where ye ſhould look, and ſee whom ye ſhould ſee, and that is a King; See him to be a King, and ſee him, as a King; for that duty is that which muſt compleat the delight of my Text, <hi>Thine eyes ſhall ſee the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, this doth ſerve to reprove them, <hi>which would quite take a King out of the world,</hi> which would not have one King for any eye to look upon; theſe are the right Baſiliskes to ſting to death the Baſilic calling. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a King ſhall be ſo farre from being <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the foundation of a Commonwealth, that he ſhall be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the miſchief, and deſtruction of a Commonwealth. Good Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth-men they are in the mean while, which take away the honour and Ornament of a Commonwealth. For a King in a Commonwealth is like the heart in the body, the root in the tree, the Spring in the ſtream, the Eagle in the skye, the Sun in the fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mament, &amp; theſe pink-eyed people look upon a King not only with diſdain, but defiance. <hi>Neque mel, neque apes;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tryphon</note> They like not the hony of Government, nor the Bee that ſhould afford it them. This wild colt that he might not be backed at all neigheth up and down in the world againſt the Rider, and ſaith,<note place="margin">Ariſtoph.</note> 
               <hi>Tolle calcar</hi> take away the very Spur. To ſuch a King is an heart-gripe, an eye-ſore, yea they can look upon their Fawnes, and <hi>Satyres, Anakims,</hi> and <hi>Zanzummims, Arbahs,</hi> and <hi>Aſhbibenobs</hi> with more delight then upon a King. What need have we of a King? what doth a King a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us? They have cried themſelves ſo long to be the free-born people of <hi>England,</hi> that they would not onely be free in reſpect of liberty, but free in reſpect of Soveraignty. Oh this ſame Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy (ſay they) is the great bondage of the world! King-ſhip,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:100932:19"/>and Goſpel-ſhip cannot ſtand together.<note place="margin">Virgil.</note> 
               <hi>Cur non Mopſe?</hi> why not brother of Chriſt? How can Chriſt be a King here, when he ſaith, that <hi>his Kingdom is not of this world?</hi> doubtleſſe theſe perſons make themſelves Angels which expect Chriſt to Reign over them? Why may not Kings here exerciſe authority, when Chriſt ſuffered them? He <hi>paid tribute to Caeſar,</hi> and wiſhed all men <hi>to give unto Caeſar, the things that are Caeſars.</hi> Why do he himſelf often com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare himſelf to a King, and call himſelf the <hi>King of Kings,</hi> if there ſhould be no ſuch thing as a King? Was is not propheſied, that Kings ſhould be <hi>nourſing Fathers to the Church?</hi> yes, and in the time of the Goſpel, it is ſaid, that <hi>Kings ſhall hate the Whore, and eat her fleſh, and burn her with fire.</hi> Rev. 17.16. and that not onely the people <hi>which are ſaved ſhould walk in the light of the new Jeruſalem, but that the Kings of the earth ſhould bring glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and honour to it.</hi> Rev. 21.24. In what one place of the whole Scripture is it ſaid that there ſhall be no Kings? no, I find it not in Holy writ, but in holy fancy, in the Acts of the Pragmatical. I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the religion of the buſineſſe is rapine, that ſuch might ſhare amongſt them the Crown-Land, &amp; every Mechanick might ſit in a Chaire of State; goodly Domination we ſhould have under ſuch Kings, their free Monarchy would be as good as their free Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery. But let them leave fulminating againſt Kings, for I do not find in the whole Bible one thunder-bolt caſt at the calling. If Scripture be their Rule, I do not ſee there but that Kings may as well enjoy their Robes, as they their unlaced Jackets. The Goſpel doth take away from none propriety, nor from Kings Prerogative. Chriſt knew that Kings would be the beſt Guardians to his Church, for from whom hath Chriſtianity received more ſuffrage and Patronage, favour and furtherance, promotion and propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion then from Kings? who were greater Foſter-fathers to Religion, then <hi>Conſtantine, Theodoſius, Justinian, Gratian, Tiberius</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, <hi>Theophilus,</hi> and many others? oh theſe were the great Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars to ſupport the building, the Torch-bearers of faith, the high Stewards in Chriſt Court, and the high Chamberlains to the ſpouſe of Chriſt Jeſus. The Church had never more Soveraignty, then by theſe pious Princes wearing the Croſs upon their Crowns. When Kings had the command of the Churches mint, there was coine truly ſtamped, we had ſince little elſe but Alchyn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y; when
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:100932:19"/>theſe Fathers begat Children to God Almighty we had a lovely Progeny, we have had ſince too many Harmaphrodites. <hi>Aliud ſceptrum, aliud plectrum.</hi> It is one thing to be a good Monarch, another thing to be a good Minſtrel, vulgar ſpirits are not fit for publick Government. <hi>Quid caeco cum ſpeculo?</hi> What ſhould a blind man do with a glaſſe? ſo what ſhould an ignorant Plebeian do with the glaſſe of Magiſtracy? <hi>Feli crocoton?</hi> ſhall the Mouſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catcher weare the Robe of honour? <hi>Alia Menecles, alia Porcel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus.</hi> The Tradeſ-man doth ſpeak of one thing, and the Prince of another. What then? is not every man fit to be a Prince, and yet are there men apt to pull down Princes, that Kings being ſtripped, Canvas-coat might weare the Robe? Alas, <hi>è ſquila non naſcitur roſa,</hi> there muſt be an <hi>indoles</hi> for Government. What then? ſhall we have Prince blown away with a whirle-wind? no, Chriſt can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſpare them; He which doth give lawes for Princes to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verenced doth not make them Out-lawes, Chriſt will not loſe his chief, and beſt ſervant out of his Family. Chriſt doth find Princes ſo beneficial to him, that his Kingdom, and their Kingdom ſhall fall together. And yet theſe Larves of profeſſion, Hob-goblins of Chriſtianity, Zanies of the Goſpel, Decoyes of faith, and Cacodae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons of a Church, what a clamour do they raiſe in the world to pull down all Princes. But they which are Arch-Diſſemble is in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things, which ſay they are all ſpirit, and yet we find them rank fleſh; which ſay they muſt not fight, and yet they are ever with a ſword in their hands; which ſay they muſt turn the other cheek alſo, and yet are ever anon fiſting our cheeks; which ſay that they deſire nothing but liberty of conſcience, &amp; yet their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe hath been to inſlave all them which are not of their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience; which ſay that they would poſſeſſe the earth as the incek, and yet have poſſeſſed the earth as the furious; theſe men as they have been equivocal in all other things, ſo much more in this of Government, for they would have no Kings, that Beggars might be Kings, not to carry the name, but to exerciſe the power of Kings to the height. To get the Scepter into their hand how turbulent, and truculent have they been? Germany hath felt enough of them by the uproars which were raiſed by <hi>Thomas Muntzer, John Buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, David Georg, Bernard Knipperdoling;</hi> &amp;c. but the ſaddeſt Tragedy hath been reſerved to be acted upon our Stage. Who
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:100932:20"/>have refled houſes, and ſteyned the land with bloud more then the Anabaptiſts, Levellers and fifth Monarchy-men? In all the wars who were more forward and fierce then theſe? whoſe voyces were louder? whoſe ſwords were ſharper? who have ſhewn more rage againſt the Kingdome, and more rancour againſt Kings? Are not theſe the men, which chaſed away our Dread Soveraign <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt of bleſſed memory from his Court? which fought againſt him to the laſt ſtroke? which when they had taken him priſoner car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried him up &amp; down the Land in Triumph? plucked him to priſon, when he was ready to be reſtored to his Throne, which ſet up an High Court of Juſtice againſt him, arraigned him, cried out for Juſtice againſt him, condemned him, and the ſaddeſt word which ever was ſpoken in Chriſtendom, beheaded him? Are not theſe the men which did vote that our Dread Soveraign <hi>Charles</hi> the ſecond of bleſſed preſence ſhould never return to his Throne, and when to aſtoniſhment he was voted in, was there not their great Champion with his Myrmidons at his heels at Edge-hill, what in him and his lay, to keep him out? &amp; when by Miracle he was brought into the Nation, were not theſe the men which have been continually murmuring, and mutining and breaking out into bloudy attempts, threatning at one time that they would deſtroy the King, and all the Royall race, and aſſayling at another time to have blunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſſed both King and Kingdome? Yet is it not to be feared, that the wild beaſt of the Forreſt ſhall be let looſe to range again? ſhall we hardly believe the Tiger to be cruel, till he hath gorged him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with a general ſlaughter? Are ſuch to be won with kindneſſe? or reclaimed with clemency? No, I am afraid that they are <hi>Cocka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trices, that will never be charmed.</hi> And yet ſome mortified man, or other will be pleading for theſe ſelf-denying brethren, ſaying this will be the laſt of their practiſes, and therefore pardon that which is paſt. Pardon? what till they daſh out our brains with a pardon in their hands? Is it pity to ſpare vermine, Leopards, Crocodiles? Beware of <hi>Sauls</hi> pity in ſparing <hi>Agag</hi> till the Kingdom be rent away for him, or of <hi>Ahabs</hi> pity in ſparing <hi>Benhadad, till life go for life.</hi> 1 Kings 20.42. Such prodigious male-contents are omi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous, and if they be not timely &amp; ſeverely puniſhed, they threaten a bloudy fate to the whole Nation, that the King ſhall be made a Sacrifice, and the Kingdom a whole Burnt-offering. What the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:100932:20"/>laſt wind-up of ſuch a connivence will be,<note place="margin">Plut.</note> 
               <hi>mox ſciemus melius vate,</hi> In a ſhort time we may know better, then if any Prophet foretold it. <hi>Post rem devoratam ratio?</hi> When all is devoured,<note place="margin">Seneca.</note> ſhall we then conſult how to preſerve our ſelves? Is not the hazard at this time great? yes, men cannot eat with comfort, nor trade with ſafety, nor walk with confidence, nor ſleep with quiet ſo long as the Canaanite is in the Land. The Kingdom cannot have peace till the head of <hi>Sheba</hi> be caſt over the walls. Let us not truſt their ſoft ſpeeches, till they have made us ſpeechleſſe, nor their pale faces, till they have made us look with griſly faces I read of Maho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metane Hermits which lived in woods as men dead to the world, till they had gotten diſciples enough about them, and they ſet upon the King of <hi>Fez,</hi> and <hi>Marocco,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Knolles in his Turk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</note> and deprived him both of Crown and life. So this critical, hypocritical generation will ſo long in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fatuate us with their tender conſciences till they cut in pieces our tender heart-ſtrings. Robes, and Rochets, Stars, and Collars of S. S. look to your ſelves, if they give but one twitch more at you, they will do their beſt to pluck them quite off, and then deride you for your Indulgence. Look not to their pretences, but to their Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxes, not to their Magical charmes, but to their bloudy Maximes. Shall we never know their tenets till we have learned them with ſhivered skuls, nor underſtand their principles till they be printed upon the Countryes dead carkaſſes? They which want good man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners we ſhall find little morality from them; they which will not ſtir their hats to us, they are ſtriking at our heads; they which have nothing but Thou in their mouthes, they do count us baſe, and tell us by that ſcorning word, that they are ready to ſhew themſelves barbarous. A little of their ſavage nature is made apparent, but they have <hi>ſeven abominations in their hearts,</hi> which were never yet diſcovered to the world. Thus much we may evidently, and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimentally conclude concerning them, that they would deſtroy all Lawyers, gibbet all Nobles, crucify all Biſhops, and decoll all Kings, and for a fair tayles ſake ſhall we ſuffer theſe Panthers to go ſcot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>free? ſhall they cut our throats with aenigmaes? and wring off our necks with Hieroglyphicks? Ah this ſame new Monarchy doth threaten to root out all old Monarchies! and theſe ſame Anaba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſts will hazard to rebaptize the Land in her own blood. What do they dream of, and what may we dread but a general Maſſacre?
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:100932:21"/>Are our wounds then ſarce healed, and ſhall we tender ſuch ſtab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers? Is common bloud-ſhed daily puniſhed with death, and ſhall we ſpare ſuch incorrigible Murtherers? If they could but repent, I would teare the heart out of my boſome if it ſhould want mercy towards them. If <hi>Saul</hi> would become <hi>Paul,</hi> I would then embrace him as a convert, as a Saint; all the havocks which have been made in the Church, and the cruel outrages for me ſhould be forgotten, and forgiven; but when their principles are no King, no lawes, no Miniſtery, no ſuperiority, no propriety, I cannot count theſe ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der conſciences, nor carry a tender conſcience towards them. Till they renounce their opinions, I do renounce them, and cannot think but all their fair words do but prepare, and fore-run (what in them ly) a foul day. They may make themſelves inſtantly ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, if they pleaſe, they would have made us abjure all Kingly Government to be lawfull, if they will but abjure that as an exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crable opinion, and give reall aſſurances, that they abhorre it, then all anger, and fear is at end, but if they perſiſt in this Tragical tenet, I know not how to pity them, which pity none but themſelves; till this be done all their Declarations are but Incantations,</p>
            <q>Fiſtula dulce canit —</q>
            <p>The pipe indeed doth play ſweetly, but it is at the Fowlers lips, and let the Birds look to their necks. If they will give us no pledges of their converſion, and fidelity, I know not why we ſhould put any confidence, or affiance in them; for the queſtion then is onely this, whether the ſecurity of Conſpiratours, or the ſecurity of the Nation be more requiſite; whether it were better to preſerve the lives of lawleſſe Malecontents, or the life of a lawfull King; if the Sages of the Nation can ſave themſelves, let them ſave them; but if all true-hearted Subjects live in daily fright of them, it were bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that they ſhould groane under juſtice, then that we ſhould groan our laſt. <hi>Becauſe ſentence against an evill work is not executed ſpeedily, therefore the hearts of the children of men are fully ſet to do evill.</hi> Eccleſ. 8.11. <hi>Vnto the horſe belongeth a whip, and to the aſſe a bridle, and a rod to the fools back.</hi> Prov. 26.3. <hi>If the wicked be worthy to be beaten, the Judge ſhall cauſe him to ly down, and to be beaten before his face.</hi> Deut. 25.2. Well, if for all this theſe muſt live, and live with this cancer in their breſts, or rather with this ſteeletto in their conſciences, yet let them go live
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:100932:21"/>where they may do no miſchief, and may not be a continual Dread. Seeing they are ſo ready to fight againſt their own Country-men, ſend them to fight againſt the great Turk; or they which are ſo ſet upon killing, let them be conveyed into ſome Iſland, where they may turn Huntſmen to kill wild beaſts, for according to their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent principles, they are fitter to go live amongſt Savages, and Wolves then amongſt men of morality, and Chriſtianity. Or yet further if the mercy of the Land muſt be the miſery of the Land, that here they muſt continue if not to our death (perhaps) yet to our terrour, then let all beware how they do conſort with them, or in the leaſt manner comply with them, for they are the peſts of States, and prodigees of Nations, they approve of no Government, they reject all Kings. And can there be greater Monſters in humane ſociety, then ſuch ſword-men againſt authority, and Headſmen to Kings? no, theſe are the worſt eyes that can be in the head of a Nation, becauſe the beſt eyes do delight in the preſence of a King, and count it an happinſſe to ſee a King, for <hi>Thine eyes ſhall ſee the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Part. <hi>In his Beauty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now let us come to the luſtre of the Gemme, <hi>the Beauty of the King, Thine eyes ſhall ſee the King in his Beauty.</hi> From hence obſerve, that <hi>the glorious King is the King ſhining in the ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour of his Royalties;</hi> not onely when an excellent title, but <hi>excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Majesty is added to him.</hi> Dan. 4.36. not onely when the Land is the Land of his inheritance, but <hi>the Land of his Dominion.</hi> 2 Chron. 8.6. not onely when he hath the chief place amongſt men, but when he hath the chief power amongſt men, when he <hi>doth rule over men.</hi> 2 Sam. 23.3. It is not the Crown, but the Crown-right, which doth make a King, otherwiſe Kingſhip is but <hi>nobilis ſervitus, a noble kind of ſervitude.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Petrus Greg. l. <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi> de rep. Eraſm. in Apoph. Sueton. in Veſpaſ. c. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Nihil beatum ſine li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertate. Nothing can be called bleſſed without liberty.</hi> Magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence without juſt power is but a golden chain. When the title is with one, and the command with others, this is rather to look upon Kings, then to live a King. Therefore was it ſaid of <hi>Veſpaſian,</hi> that when newes was brought him concerning the accidents which had happened to <hi>Vitellius,</hi> that <hi>a certain Majesty aroſe in his
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:100932:22"/>countenance, which was never ſeen before,</hi> which did fore-tell, that ere long he ſhould be Emperour. The Majeſty of a King then is the true Inauguration of a King, for what is Majeſty, but <hi>Major pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtas,</hi> the greater power? Deprive a King then of his Royal power, and men had as good pluck the Crown from his Head, this is truly <hi>Crimen laeſae Majestatis,</hi> that though men never-touch the Kings Perſon, yet they touch his Majeſty, and this haughtineſſe of it ſelf is high treaſon. <hi>If I be a Father where is my honour?</hi> So if there be a King, where is his Royalty? <hi>Thoſe things, which do imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately pertain to a King ſhould have an inherent dignity in them,</hi> yea,<note place="margin">Valer. M. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> it is not fitting <hi>reliquias Regis jacere inhonoratas,</hi> that the very Reliques of a King ſhould remain without honour, as <hi>Val. Maximus</hi> ſaith concerning <hi>Perſes. Traſeas,</hi> though a great Prieſt in Rome was accuſed, becauſe he was not preſent in the beginning of the year to take the ſolemn Oath to the Emperour,<note place="margin">Tacit. l. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> nor did ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear at the publication of the publick vowes for his health. So any thing which tends to the diminution of a Kings honour is repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſibile, and criminal. <hi>Cicero</hi> pleading for <hi>Deiotarus</hi> a King, ſaith, <hi>Semper in hac civitate regium nomen ſanctum fuit.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tull. orat. pro Deio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taro.</note> The name of a King was ever holy in this City. So that is the beſt City and Country, where the name of a King is moſt Sacred, &amp; the perſon of a King moſt reverenced. Wherefore doth the Scripture ſay, <hi>Fear God, and honour the King,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.17. but that God would have a King to be honoured, as well as himſelf to be feared? There was a cuſtome in Lacedemonia that men ſhould riſe up to none but the King,<note place="margin">Neracli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des in La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedem. rap.</note> and the <hi>Ephori,</hi> and doubtleſſe a diſtinct veneration do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to Kings. He that doth take away from a King his prepoten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Supremacy had as good ſteal the Crown Jewels. The <hi>Voon,</hi> that is the King of <hi>Japonia</hi> had a ponyard lying on the one ſide of his Throne, and a bow and arrowes on the other ſide of his Throne, to ſhew that they which did wound the Kings honour were fit to be diſpatched out of the world,<note place="margin">Ioh. M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellus.</note> and I think that our Kings have a Scepter, and a Sword for the ſame end. <hi>Facilem ſe praebeat Princeps,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Calliſtrat. l. <hi>5.</hi> co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guit. <hi>§, 1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſed contemni non patiatur.</hi> Let a Prince ſhew himſelf affable to the people, but let him not ſuffer himſelf to be contemned. For if he hath loſt his dignity, he is a King, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Royalty. An arrogant Courtier, or an inſolent Stateſman that is too bold with the Kings power is next to a Rebel, which doth
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:100932:22"/>fight againſt him with an armed hand. A wiſe counſel is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite for a King, but counſel had need have in it two grains of modeſty to one of direction. If it troubled <hi>David</hi> ſo much that he had cut off the lap of <hi>Sauls</hi> garment, then how may it trouble them which cut off half of the Robe of Majeſty,<note place="margin">Tacit. l. <hi>1.</hi> annal.</note> 
               <hi>Auctoritas Principis nata est ex metu &amp; admiratione.</hi> The authority of a Prince is begotten of fear, and admiration. When a King then hath loſt his dread and reverence he is but a painted Sun. <hi>Vulgus facile in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoleſcit.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Q. Curt. l. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> The vulgar is apt to grow inſolent, but this audaciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is to be repreſſed.<note place="margin">Ariſt. l. <hi>5.</hi> polit. c. <hi>11.</hi> Dio. Caſſ. l. <hi>52.</hi> hiſt.</note> Therefore <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> would not have too much honours given to Subjects, leſt they ſhould hold themſelves Compeers with their Prince. <hi>Periculoſum ſemper est nomen priva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti hominis ſupra principis attolli,</hi> It is ever perillous for the name of any private man to be equalled, or preferred before the Prince. <hi>Majeſtas in Principe est velut anima regni.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Seneca l. <hi>1.</hi> de Clem. Dio Caſſ. l. <hi>41.</hi> hiſtor.</note> Majeſty in a Prince is as it were the ſoul of the Kingdom. <hi>Quam tuta navigatio est, ubi nautae gubernatori non pareant?</hi> what ſafe ſayling is there where the Mariners do not obey the Ship-Maſter? Contempt is as great a ſeeds-man of rebellion as hatred, for the one is begotten of ambition as well as the other of diſcontent. It was contempt which raiſed up <hi>Arſaces</hi> againſt <hi>Sardanapalus, Dion</hi> againſt <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſius, Cyrus</hi> againſt <hi>Aſtyages,</hi> and <hi>Senthes</hi> againſt <hi>Amadocus,</hi> oh it is an heavy thing when,</p>
            <q>
               <l>—ſubverſa jacebit</l>
               <l>Pristina Majestas ſoliorum,<note place="margin">Plut. in Rom. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poph. O Remp. brevi pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituram, in quâ vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultant. populus autem, &amp; imperitae plebeculae decernit. P. Crinit. l. <hi>1.</hi> de ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt. diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plin. c. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> —</l>
            </q>
            <p>When the Majeſty of Thrones come to be ſubverted. <hi>Coturnix a Quayle</hi> ſaith <hi>Heſychius</hi> doth come of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, both which words do ſignify a bird, as if a Quayle were the bird of birds, now one of theſe Quayles fighting with many birds remaining Conquerour over all, <hi>Erotheus</hi> the Procuratour of Egypt bought, and thinking that it was as good in taſt, as in fighting, he kild it, and eat it, which <hi>Augustus Caeſar</hi> hearing of, he ſent for <hi>Ero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theus</hi> and nailed him to a ſhipmaſt, becauſe for his appetite he had deſtroyed a Victorious Bird. If he were ſo ſeverely puniſhed which abuſed a Royal Bird, then what may they deſerve, which abaſe, and vilipend Royal Dignity? <hi>Petrus Crinitus</hi> hath a notable diſcourſe, that when <hi>Anacharſis</hi> came to Athens, and ſaw the Princes but onely giving counſell for things to be done, &amp; the people decreeing
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:100932:23"/>all, he cried out, <hi>Oh Commonwealth in a ſhort time coming to ruin, where the Princes propound things, and the people determine them!</hi> So if a Prince be not Superiour in command it is to take in pieces the joints of a Throne, and to bring down a King that ſhould or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der all to the wills of Inferiours<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Let as much honour as can be be given to faithfull Counſell, but ſtill let the Prerogative be invio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable. It is good adviſe, if well liſtened to, which is given in the 8. of Eccleſ. 2. <hi>I advertiſe thee to take heed to the Kings Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that in reſpect of the Oath of God,</hi> becauſe God hath precepted, and ſwore a whole Kingdom to the Commandement of a King. For wherefore is he a King, if he ſhould ſtand by to ſee his Commands vilified, and neglected? would a maſter of the anvile, or the awle, or the frippery wares be thus uſed? Let every one then have his right, <hi>honour to whom honour belongeth,</hi> Royalty to whom Royalty belongeth. If a King doth want his juſt authority he is but an appellative King. For what is it to ſee a King weare Robes, ſit in a Throne, hold a Scepter, if he doth want his Soveraignty? this is but to ſee a King in his Bravery, and not a King in his Beauty. In beauty there muſt be no skarre, ſo in the Government no reſtraint of juſt authority. He is never a compleat King, till there be <hi>inconcuſſa libertas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amb. Petrarch.</note> unſhaken liberty in governing. <hi>Leo ubicunque est, Leo est,</hi> A Lion whereſoever he be, he is a Lion; ſo a King wherſoever he be he muſt be reigning. The King muſt give the word to the whole Nation, all muſt <hi>incline to follow him.</hi> Judg. 9.3. <hi>they must be at his bidding.</hi> 1 Sam. 22.14. <hi>At his word they must go out, and at his word they must come in.</hi> Num. 27.21. They muſt move forward, &amp; backward, as he doth give the charge A reſplendent King is he which is Imperial, which is powerfull in having his Mandates obſerved, This is a King in his beauty. <hi>Thine eyes ſhall ſee the King in his Beauty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">Applic.</note> that the triall of Bleſſings is in the beauty of them; not the enjoyment of a thing, but the qualification of a thing is that which makes it comfortable; many things are poſſeſſed, but the heart taſts not the true ſweetneſſe of them, for they come maymed, or defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive. <hi>Tully</hi> doth call that <hi>Decorum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cic. l. <hi>1.</hi> off.</note> a comely thing, which hath in it that which is <hi>naturae conſentaneum,</hi> agreeable to the nature of it, for if there be not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that which is convenient, there can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that which is beautifull; the Hebricians doe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rive
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:100932:23"/>beauty from congruity,<note place="margin">Kiſchron a Gaſcher.</note> ſo that which do come ſhort of the juſt aptitudes doth ſuffer an high diminution in the nature and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of a bleſſing. And how many of theſe half-faced bleſſings are there? as God gives a man wit, and no diſcretion; birth, and no generoſity of ſpirit; gifts, and no faith; zeale, and no conſcience; do not the Scripture ſpeak of ſuch unhappy bleſſings? yes, <hi>of houſes without a man,</hi> 9. Iſ. 6. <hi>of a womb, but barren,</hi> 9. Hoſ. 14. <hi>of ſheep without a ſhepheard.</hi> Num. 27.17. <hi>of a man to whom God hath given riches, treaſures, and honour, and he wanteth nothing for his ſoul of all that it deſireth, but God giveth him not power to eat thereof, but a ſtranger eat it up.</hi> Eccleſ. 6.2. how then can theſe be proper bleſſings? no, they have a blemiſh; <hi>&amp; quod est de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme nihil ornare potest,</hi> That which is deformed nothing (in the ſtate that it is in) can adorne it. Search thy bleſſings then, whether they be true bleſſings; thou maiſt enjoy ſome things, that may be ſickneſſes to thee, yea cockatrices egges hatched to ſting thee to death; a fire not blown may conſume thee in the poſſeſſion of them. Job 20.26. God may caſt abominable filth upon thee by them. Nahum. 3.6. ye may be able to feaſt richly, and your <hi>Tables may be made a ſnare, and your proſperity a ruine.</hi> Pſ. 69.22. ye may be heirs to plentifull eſtates, which your progenitours have gotten by uſury, bribery, extortion, ſacriledge, and God may <hi>lay the ſorrow of the Fathers upon the children.</hi> Job 21.19. ye may have fortified your ſelves in wicked courſes, and drawn in the ſtrength of the Land to defend you in damnable deſignes, and yet <hi>ye may be cast down in the midst,</hi> Micah 6.14. and though ye have had never ſo many <hi>Hectors</hi> on your ſide, yet your puiſſant Stabbers may become puſillanimous, for <hi>the ſtout-hearted are ſpoyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, they have ſlept their ſleep, and all the men of might have not found their hands.</hi> Pſ. 76.5. ye may have raiſed up falſe worſhips in the Nation, and have had notable ſucceſſe in beguiling unſtable ſouls, but your ſorcereſſe <hi>Jezabel</hi> may be caſt out at the window; <hi>For they ſhall prevail no longer, but their madneſſe ſhall be made manifest to all men.</hi> 2 Tim. 3.9. <hi>The thorne, and the thistle may come upon your Altars.</hi> Hoſ. 10.8. Bleſſe not your ſelves then in every thing, which doth carry the appearance of a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, for I do read that God does turn <hi>many bleſſings into curſes.</hi> Mal. 2.2.</p>
            <q>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:100932:24"/>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Euripid. Trag. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
            </q>
            <p>To a man that is now called ſhiningly happy there may inſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly come ſad changes. <hi>Alexander</hi> wrot letters in the height of his fortunes to <hi>Antipater</hi> by a Meſſenger called <hi>Athlius, Diogenes</hi> ſtanding by when the letters were delivered, what ſaith he, doth <hi>Alexander</hi> ſend letters by <hi>Athlius?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bruſon l. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> this doth ſhew that he will be unfortunate, for <hi>Athlius ad Athlium per Athlium,</hi> He which will be unfortunate doth ſent letters to him that may be unfortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, by him, that is named Unfortunate. So a mans welfare that wants the complexion of Gods bleſſing in the face of it, let him com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend it to one of his deareſt Complices, yet <hi>Athlius</hi> carryes the meſſage, and there is nothing but unfortunate to be expected to the man, or his Adherents. Suſpect thy bleſſings then, till thou haſt examined the viſages of them, and thou findeſt them by God to be made truly amiable; elſe they may be too hot for thy hands, thou maiſt drink poyſon in a ſweet draught, thou maiſt ſwallow down a hook with the bait, the moth may be got into them, the line of confuſion may be ſtretched over them; as great heaps as thou haſt gathered together God may fan in the gate of the Land; as fair locks as thou haſt, God may bring his raſour upon thy head; as boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterous as thou haſt been, God may run upon thee like a Gyant; he may blow upon all that thou haſt, make thy heels bare, and ſend thee to go ſeek thy bread out of deſolate places. It is not the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing then, but the <hi>Beauty</hi> of the bleſſing which doth make it tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly happy; a miſhapen bleſſing is like <hi>Moah, a veſſell wherein there is no pleaſure.</hi> Jer. 48.38. God does not alwayes promote men to afford them true felicity, no, he raiſes up men for a while at laſt to make <hi>their image deſpiſed.</hi> Pſal. 73.20. and to draw them from their ceiled parlours, where they have been beaking their ſelves by their bright, and ſparkling fires, to a cold, dark place, where there ſhall be <hi>neither coals to warm them, nor light to ſit by.</hi> Iſ. 47.14. See then how a curſe may purſue you after all the proſperity that ye have enjoyed; if ye want the comelineſſe of a bleſſing, ye want the comfort of it, as here it was not enough for God to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent as a bleſſing to his deareſt people, that they ſhould have liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty with their eyes to ſee a King, but they ſhould ſee the King <hi>in his Beauty. Thine eyes ſhall ſee the King in his Beauty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:100932:24"/>
Secondly, this doth ſhew unto us, that <hi>God can give us beautifull bleſſings, Oh how plenteous is the goodneſſe that thou haſt laid up in ſtore for them that fear thee!</hi> yea, <hi>quam pulchra tabernacula, O Jacob! How beautifull, or goodly are thy tents oh Jacob! and thy habitations oh Iſrael! The ſpark of the wicked ſhall not ſhine.</hi> Job. 18.5. but the righteous ſhall be a ſhining people. <hi>Light is ſown for the righteous,</hi> Pſ. 97.11. <hi>Ariſe oh Jeruſalem and be bright,</hi> Iſ. 60.1. for Gods face do ſhine upon his ſervants, and his candle do ſo ſhine upon their heads that their very pathes do ſhine, <hi>the beauty of the Lord their God is upon them.</hi> Pſ. 90.17. <hi>yea their name is ſpread among the heathen, for their beauty, and they are made perfect through his beauty.</hi> Ezech. 16.14. <hi>Gods bleſſings give them a fair neck.</hi> Hoſ. 10.11. <hi>make their faces purer then ſnow, whiter then milk, more ruddy then Rubies, or the poliſhed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phir.</hi> Lam. 4.7. yea they are ſo adorned, and decked, as if they had <hi>a beautifull Crown upon their heads.</hi> Ezech. 16.12. oh then that we would ſerve God in the beauty of holineſſe; what amiable bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings might we enjoy under him? for, <hi>How great is his goodneſſe! and how great is his beauty!</hi> Zach. 9.17. that is, the goodneſſe of his mercies, and the beauty of his benefits; his favour is ſplendour, his bounty is beauty, Oh that we would be good we ſhould find God goodneſſe it ſelf. <hi>The hand of the Lord is upon all them that ſeek him in goodneſſe.</hi> Ezra 8.22. <hi>they which ſeek the Lord want nothing that is good.</hi> Pſ. 34.10. <hi>He giveth to all men liberally, and reproacheth no man.</hi> James 1.5. <hi>He loadeth us with benefits.</hi> Pſ. 68.19. <hi>he will pour out bleſſings till there ſhall be no room to receive them.</hi> Mal. 3.10. <hi>They which diligently obey the voice of the Lord, and obſerve, and do all his Commandments, all theſe bleſſings ſhall come upon them, and overtake them.</hi> Deut. 28.1, 2. yea where, and in what ſhall they not be bleſſed? <hi>They ſhall be bleſſed in the City, and in the field, in the fruit of their body, and in the fruit of their ground, in their basket, and in their dough, and in their ſtore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſes, and in all that they ſet their hand unto; their enemies that riſe up against them ſhall fall before them, they ſhall come out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them one way, and flee from them ſeven wayes, they ſhall be the head, &amp; not the tail, above, and not beneath, be able to lend, and not to borrow, yea their God will open his good treaſure, and leave ſuch characteriſing marks of his bounty, that all the people of the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:100932:25"/>earth ſhall ſee that the name of the Lord is called upon by them, and they ſhall be afraid of them,</hi> Deut. 28.10. or as it in Iſ. 61.9. <hi>Their ſeed ſhall be known amongst the Gentiles, and their buds a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst the people. All that ſee them, ſhall know them, that they are the ſeed, which the Lord hath bleſſed.</hi> Iſ. 61.9. yea, it is Gods goodneſſe which maketh him ſo appetible, goodneſſe is the proper object of his will, as if he had not a will in him, but to communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the effluxes of his kindneſſe, and favour to his dear ones; by that he is not onely a free Agent, and ſo doth nothing out of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity, but a liberal Agent, becauſe he does act good with an emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency. <hi>God is love,</hi> John 1.4. becauſe he hath nothing but love in him, there is <hi>praeceptum, Conſilium, &amp; operatio boni in Deo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tho. Aq. <hi>1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> q. <hi>19.</hi> a. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, counſel, and operation of good in God. Yea, whereas many other affections are but in God interpretatively, according to the ſimilitude of the effect, love is God properly, and eſſentially, for it is the firſt motion of his will; yea, joy and delight, deſire and hope are not ſo properly in God as love, becauſe all theſe are but ema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of it, they having love for their ſpring, or root. It is ſuch a ſweet property, that whereſoever it doth affect it cannot but be diſperſing,<note place="margin">Tho. Aq. <hi>1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> q. <hi>20.</hi> a. <hi>2.</hi> Aſsidet Deo, &amp; magna eſt cum ipſo neceſsitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juncta. Nyſſ. in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rat. de pauper. am. &amp; benig. omp Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Dei memoria ſufficiens eſt ad virtutum laborem. Chryſ. hom. <hi>67.</hi> in Gen. Sunt ut divitum filii qui ornaius gratia au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eum monile geſtant, &amp; nunquam deponunt, veluti nobilitat is ſignum circumferentes, &amp; oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intes. Chryſ hom. <hi>1.</hi> ad Philippenſes.</note> and exhibiting, for <hi>amare nihil est, niſivelle bonum alicui,</hi> to love is nothing but to will good to another. Therefore love is implanted into God, and hath a neceſſary connexion with him, for ſo long as he is a God, he cannot but be a beneficent God; the effects of this love are ſo numerous and conſpicuous, <hi>that the memory of Gods favours, is work enough for all the vertues.</hi> Find me out Gods true Favourites, and I wil ſoon ſhew you their rich Largeſſes, <hi>like Noble-mens children they never walk abroad, but they carry their Jewel of honour about their necks. Cleomenes,</hi> and <hi>Ptolomaeus,</hi> which had the ſirnames of <hi>Euergetae,</hi> were never comparable to our benigne God, for <hi>he does exceeding aboundantly above all that we can ask, or think, there is no end of his goodneſs.</hi> As <hi>Plutarch</hi> reports of <hi>Timoleon</hi> that he rejoyced <hi>tam immenſam mult it udinem hominum vitam agere beatam ſuâ opera,</hi> that ſuch a multitude of men lived an happy life by his means; ſo it is Gods delight that he hath ſuch a multitude of Courtiers which are ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteined
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:100932:25"/>by his penſions. Oh then that ye would ſerve God, what might ye not receive of his bounty? ye <hi>might mount upon the high places of the earth, the Crownes might then be to Helem.</hi> The golden phial with rich treaſure which <hi>Aemilius</hi> beſtowed upon <hi>Tubero</hi> for his ſervice in the war againſt <hi>Perſeus;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Plut. in Paulo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Cromer. l. <hi>5.</hi> Sabell. l. <hi>5.</hi> En. <hi>3.</hi> Diodor. Sic. l. <hi>17.</hi> Sab. l. <hi>2.</hi> En. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> the golden hand which <hi>Boleſlaus</hi> the thrid of Hungary gave unto <hi>Zeliſlaus</hi> for a hand which he had loſt in a fight againſt the Moravians; the golden bullock, which <hi>Lucius Minutius</hi> received for deſtroying <hi>Sp. Melius;</hi> the high priviledges, and preſents which <hi>Cyrus</hi> ſent to the <hi>Arimaſpi</hi> for their relieving him at an exigent; the infinite gifts which <hi>Xerxes</hi> beſtowed upon <hi>Pythius</hi> the Phrygian for en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaining his whole Army, were never like to the Donatives, and Benevolences which we might receive from God. But here is our baſeneſſe, that we look for every thing that is beautifull, but will do nothing which is beautifull, where is our beautifull repentance, innocency, devotion, watchfulneſſe, meditation? alas no, the Apoſtle may ſay, <hi>If any things be comely, ſeek after thoſe things,</hi> but we are not for theſe venuſt, and ſpecious things, whereby we might affect Gods eyes, or enflame his deſires towards us; we are very prompt at filthy things, filthy ſpeech, filthy luſts, filthy vomits, filthy lucre (our conſciences are defiled, and our converſations diſteined) but for doing any thing which might be acceptable and amiable, which might pleaſe Gods ſight, and ingratiate us into his favour, we have no skill in it. So that ye ſee what it is that does diminiſh your feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city, and make you walk up and down with your ſemi-proſperity, namely, becauſe ye will not be eminently Godly. There is not a more auſpicious thing in the world then Religion. Oh ye muſt fetch welfare into the Nation with your watery eyes, and bended knees, and mortified breſts, and cleanſed conſciences, and regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate fruits; your zeal in your Churches, and cloſets, and bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chambers would do more good, then all counſel-chambers. A few penitents, and Saints would be better Patriots then all the States<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in the Land. If ye would forſake your brutiſh lives, and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual courſes, your hypocriſy, and faction, your Church-ſpleen, and Liturgy-ſpight, reſtore your ill-gotten goods, and ſacrilegious poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſions, build Hoſpitals, erect Colledges, found Churches, free your ſhops from fraud, and your Tribunals from bribery, have leſs pride, and more charity amongſt you, what a glorious Kingdom might
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:100932:26"/>ye here have? Is not the Kingdom ſo happy as ye could wiſh it to be? then leave accuſing of Governours, and preſcribing of rules, and proſecuting your ſeditious bents, and ſettle the Nation upon the firſt foundation ſtone upon which it was called a Reformed Church. I believe thoſe bleſſed Martyis had in them more purity, then all the Saints that have come after them, it is no good man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to ſay that the fore-Fathers wanted a little of the childrens wit, or integrity. Had men paſt through their flames, I would think they might equal them in fervour and ſincerity, but I cannot en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure whole skins to rectify that which their Anceſtours bequeathed to after-ages with ſuch a flaming ſacrifice. Thoſe Martyrs ſtakes are more precious to me, then all the holocauſts of zeal which I have ſeen upon the Altar ſince. I would wiſh no other Heaven then they do enjoy, nor deſire any purer Religion, then they preached to ſucceſſion out of that flagrant pulpit; give me <hi>Elias</hi> mantle, which he left behind him, when he was carried a way in the fiery Chariot. I would think to ſee a prime Kingdom, if I could ſee the primitive Proteſtant. There were never ſuch fervent Preachers ſince, neither can we find ſuch Zelots. Away then with the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of <hi>Aſhdod,</hi> and let us ſpeak the true language of Canaan; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with paſſion againſt innocent Ceremonies, and let us double this indignation againſt branded hypocriſy, and curſed impiety. Let us renew the Martyrs ſanctity, and this Land may be the joy of the whole earth. Virtue would adorn the Nation, grace would beautify it, let us be beautifull Saints, and God hath beautifull bleſſings for us, even a King in his beauty. <hi>Thine eyes ſhall ſee the King in his Beauty,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, this doth ſhew that <hi>there is no Governour amiable, which doth want Beauty.</hi> There is no ill face like to an ill Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, there is no deformed Morian, or Monſter like unto a wicked Ruler, <hi>When the wicked are in authority the people ſigh.</hi> Prov. 29.2. oh it is a wofull thing when <hi>Princes are rebellions, and companions of thieves.</hi> Iſ. 1.23. for then <hi>They hunt every man his brother with a net.</hi> Micah. 7.2. and <hi>The wicked devoureth the man that is more righteous then himſelf.</hi> Hab. 1.13. <hi>They pant after the dust of the earth over the head of the poor, and turn aſide the way of the meek.</hi> Amos 2.7. <hi>They drink up the deep waters, and fowle the rest with their feet.</hi> Ezech. 34.18. <hi>In their skirts is found the Bloud of the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:100932:26"/>ſouls of poor Innocents.</hi> Jer. 2.34. <hi>When wicked men riſe up men hide themſelves.</hi> Prov. 28.28. <hi>There is a lamentation upon the houſe-tops.</hi> Jer. 48.38. <hi>All faces gather blackneſs.</hi> Jocl 2.8. <hi>They eat their bread with quaking, and drink their water with trembling.</hi> Ezek. 12.28. <hi>Their nights of pleaſure are turned into fear.</hi> Iſ. 21.4. and well may they, for not man ſeemeth then to be the Ruler, but ſome ſavage Beaſt, <hi>a Leopard watcheth over the Cities.</hi> Jer. 5.6. <hi>A Lion teareth in pieces for his whelps, and ſtrangleth for his Lion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and filleth his holes with prey, and his dens with ravine.</hi> Nah. 2.12. Then <hi>nihil abſurdum, quod utile,</hi> nothing is abſurd,<note place="margin">Thucyd. l. <hi>6.</hi> Polyb. hiſt. l. <hi>8.</hi> Appian. l. <hi>2.</hi> de bel. civ. Iornand. de red. Get. Herod. l. <hi>3.</hi> Xiphil. in vit. Ant. Carac. Plutarch. Val. M. l. <hi>9.</hi> c. <hi>2.</hi> Sueton. in Vitel.</note> that is profitable, and <hi>inimiciſſimi ſunp qui libertati patrocinantur,</hi> They are counted moſt ſpightfull againſt authority which do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend their liberty. <hi>Satellites ſunt commune maleficium,</hi> The ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diery are then a common bane. Such a Ruler <hi>ambitum ſuum bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chio metitur,</hi> doth meaſure his ambition by his arm, if he doth not want force, he will want neither title nor treaſure. <hi>Optimis invidet, deterrimis delectatur,</hi> He is ever envious againſt the worthyes and delighted moſt with Miſcreants. Then with <hi>Caracalla</hi> their ſword is their Rent-gatherer, and with <hi>Simonides</hi> they had rather want friends then mony; then they ſprinkle (with <hi>Mithridates</hi> their hoſpital gods) with bloud, and with <hi>Vitellius</hi> they think no odour upon earth ſo ſweet as the ſmell of an enemies carkaſſe. Have not we had triall ſufficient of this? yes, men which ſtroked us till they got upon our backs, &amp; then gave us enough of the ſpur; which cried up the Goſpel, and made Tradeſ-men Preachers; which talked much of the purity of faith, and brought in blaſphemy; which would ſet up Chriſtianity by pulling down Churches, and fill the Nation with wiſdome by deſtroying the Univerſities; which would help the people to freedome by free quarter, and adminiſter juſtice by taking away the lawes; which would take Tyranny out of the Land by multiplying Taxes, and confirm inheritances by ſequeſtration; which would convert men without a conference, and draw people out of darkneſſe by a light within them; which a horred coremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, and brought in imaginations, and reformed a Church, by plucking out her heart; which would ſettle us in peace by laying us in priſon, and ſend us to Heaven, by climing Gibbets. Now is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>any <hi>Beauty</hi> in this Government? as much as there is in a viper, and a Crocodilt, Whenſoever ye have ſuch Uſurpers enter your houſes
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:100932:27"/>look to have your keyes wrung out of your hands, whenſoever ſuch Executioners come expect nothing but the loſſe of your necks. Oh meddle not with them then that <hi>are given to change,</hi> be not Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federates with them, which would ſet up an unlawfull Governour, for ye had as good bring into the Nation a Tormentour, or an Headſman; an unjuſt Ruler can never be amiable, no, the true <hi>Beauty</hi> is in the legitimate Magiſtrate, the King. <hi>Thine eyes ſhall ſee the King in his Beauty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, this doth ſhew <hi>that a right King is a rare Beauty.</hi> For can the eye of man behold a more choice Object upon earth, then a lawfull and righteous King? no, when <hi>the righteous are in authority the people rejoyce,</hi> Prov. 29.2. for ſuch an one is <hi>the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister of God for good.</hi> Rom. 13.4. when <hi>a King doth reign in ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and Princes rule in judgement, that man ſhall be an hiding place from the wind, and a refuge from the tempest, as rivers of water in a dry place, and as the ſhadow of a rock in a weary Land, the eyes of the ſeeing ſhall not be ſhut, and the eares of them that hear ſhall hearken, the heart of the fooliſh ſhall underſtand know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and the tongue of the ſtutterers ſhall ſpeak diſtinctly,</hi> Iſ. 32.1, 2, 3, 4. yea, and it followeth in the 16, 17, 18. v. of that chapter, that in ſuch a Kings dayes <hi>judgement ſhall dwell in the deſart, and juſtice ſhall remaine in the fruitfull field, the work of juſtice ſhall be peace, even the work of juſtice, and quietneſſe, and aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, for ever, yea the people ſhall dwell in the tabernacle of peace and in ſure dwellings, and ſafe reſting-places.</hi> Now theſe words though they be ſpoken myſtically of Chriſt, yet literally they are meant of any good King; for a good King how beneficial is he? <hi>A King by iudgement maintaineth the Countrey.</hi> Pro. 29.4. for he knoweth that he is therefore conſtituted King, that he might <hi>do equity, and righteouſneſſe</hi> 1. Kings. 10.9. and therefore is a Copy of the Law put into his hand, that he may learne <hi>to feare the Lord his God, and keepe all the words of the Law, and the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances.</hi> Deut. 17.19. Such a King will be like <hi>David, who fed Jacob his people and Jſrael his inheritance, with a faithfull and true heart, and ruled them prudently with all his power.</hi> Pſ. 78.72.73. <hi>Or like Aſah who made a covenant with his people to ſeek the Lord God of his Fathers, with all their heart, and with all their ſoul, inſomuch that he that would not ſeek the Lord God
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:100932:27"/>of Iſrael ſhould be ſlayne, whether he be ſmall, or great, man, or woman.</hi> 2. Chron. 15.12.13. or like <hi>Jehoſaphat who walked in the firſt wayes of his Father David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Melius eſt civita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem regi à viro opti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo, quam à lege op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timâ. Ariſt. po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litic. l. <hi>1.</hi> Pictor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignis qui non tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los, &amp; fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciem, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginem va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietate co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtat. Franc patr. Sen. de inſtit. regis l. <hi>2.</hi> tit. <hi>1.</hi> Sedente in ſe immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tali Iudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te p. Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mil l. <hi>5.</hi> Regum o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culis effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacia ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam vim ineſt. P. Iovius hiſt. l. <hi>2.</hi> Herodot. l. <hi>2.</hi> Diodor. l. <hi>12.</hi> Ced. Rhod. l. <hi>19.</hi> c. <hi>29.</hi> Sigon. l. <hi>20.</hi> occid. Imp. Evagr. l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>13.</hi> Alex. ab Alex. l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>9.</hi> Herodot. l. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>and ſought the Lord God of his Fathers, and walked in his Commandments, and not after the trade of Iſrael.</hi> 2 Chron. 17.3, 4. A good King doth chiefly look <hi>to have his Throne establiſhed by righteouſneſſe.</hi> Prov. 25.5. and that <hi>his people under him may lead a peaceable, and a quiet life in all godlineſſe, and honeſty.</hi> I. Tim. 2.2. This is a good King, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed his worth, and value is ſcarcely known; A good King is like a good Spring, a good mine, a good corner-ſtone, a good Magazine, a good Angel, which made <hi>Aristotle</hi> to ſay, that it were better <hi>for a City to be governed by the best man, then by the best law,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe his life is a Law, and there need no other precept, but his precedent. He <hi>is the rare Painter which maketh his whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom a picture drawn out with Orient Colours.</hi> He is ſo transformed into God, that (as <hi>Ludovicus Craſſus</hi> wiſhed his ſon) the <hi>people may ſee the immortal Judge ſitting in him.</hi> Which made <hi>Paulus Jovius</hi> to ſay that <hi>Kings had distinct eyes from other men,</hi> becauſe they look out with their Princely eyes minding onely the general benefit. Such a Prince doth remedy the errours of former Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as <hi>Micerinus</hi> did the high enormities of <hi>Cheops,</hi> and <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phren</hi> which reigned before him in Aegypt. In ſuch an ones Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment people leave groaning, and there are nothing but <hi>laeta &amp; fauſta,</hi> pleaſant and delightfull things to be ſeen, at it was ſaid of <hi>Sitalces;</hi> or all grievances being removed, the Nation liveth <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, without fear, or perplexity, as it was ſaid of the reign of <hi>Alcimus.</hi> That wiſe Governour doth make it his prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal art to reſtore the ancient glory of a Nation, as <hi>Justinian</hi> the great did, or like that famous <hi>Tiberius</hi> the ſecond, he hath no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Princely ambition in his breſt, but that none of his predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours might exceed him in piety or felicity. That Prince is ſo ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured by the people, that like another <hi>L. Pifo</hi> becauſe he had done all things for the welfare of the Nation he ſhall be ſirnamed <hi>Frugi, the Profitable,</hi> yea, there are prayers made by the whole Land, that ſuch an one may not dye childleſſe, leſt ſuch a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned family ſhould periſh (as it is ſaid of <hi>Ariſton</hi> the King of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:100932:28"/>Lacedemonia) and if God ſend an heire, for the Fathers virtues they are willing to have the childs name called <hi>Demarathus,</hi> the peoples Darling; And well may it be ſo, for a good King doth take his Crown out of Gods hand, and doth weare it for his honour; his heart is in Heaven, and his eye is upon the Church; he doth firſt ſeek for the purity of religion, and is carefull that ſacrifices with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out blemiſh be brought to the Altar; he doth look to conquer rather with his bended knees, then his armed hand; he doth love his No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and not deſpiſe his Commons; he doth prefer a penitent be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Peere, and a juſt liver before an high-borne Grandee; he doth deſire to have his Prieſts undefiled, and his Judges uncorrupt; he doth want no Majeſty, and yet doth abound in humanity; his ſpeech is gentle, and his hand is ſoft; he is paſſionate againſt incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rigible ſinners, and yet compaſſionate to remorſe-full enemies; he grieveth at intemperance, and hateth blaſphemy; he liketh neither the laughing Projectour, nor the weeping Sectary; he would have his Sanctuary without indevotion, and his treaſury without in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury; his watchfull conſcience is the Squire of his body, and his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>precatory petitions his beſt Life-guard; his innocent life is his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graven Image, and his pious examples his richeſt Medals; he doth ſhine like a Sun himſelf, and doth wiſh to have none but bright Stars about him; next to his own pure heart he doth endeavour to have a pure Court; he doth ſtand upon his own prerogative, but catch at none of his people liberties; he had rather gild a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, then his Exchequer; his Crown-land doth ſatisfy him better then breaking an Incloſure; he can ſee a Vine-yard out of his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace-Window without proclaiming himſelf Owner of it by an <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habs</hi> evidence; he would have the liberal Arts to flouriſh, and make (if it were poſſible) every Mechenick a Lord of a Mannour; he gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth all furtherances for free Trade, and quick Merchandiſe; he hoth affect none but the generous, and ſcorn none but the proud; he doth commiſerate the wants of the poor, and he would have the rich to build them Alms-houſes; he is wiſe, and not vain glorious, valiant, and yet would never fight, chaſt, and yet not an Hermit, ſober, and yet no water-drinker, liberal, and yet not profuſe; he is ofteneſt at his Chappel, and oft at his Council-Table; he hath a liſtening ear to juſt petitions, but not to pragmatical motions; his heart is ſet upon nothing more then repairing decayed places, and
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:100932:28"/>erecting Monuments; he would leave behind him a glorious Church, and a ſetled Kingdom; he doth govern for God upon earth, that he may Reign with God in Heaven. Now is not the preſence of ſuch a King an Heavenly preſent? hath the rich hand of God a dearer pledge of favour to beſtow upon his Boſome friends? are all the ſplendid <hi>Spectacles</hi> of a Kingdom like to the face of ſuch a Prince? no, doubtleſſe he doth ſurpaſſe them all <hi>as far as light doth excell darkneſſe;</hi> oh then how may all his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects have delight under his ſhadow, and clap their hands together that they ſive to ſee ſuch happy dayes, his name may be pleaſure, his Reign Triumph, for when their eyes ſee ſuch a King, they ſee a King in his <hi>Beauty. Thine eyes ſhall ſee the King in his Beauty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fifthly, this doth reprove <hi>the blind rage of a Conſpiratour in oppoſing ſuch a King, he doth ſtrike at the Beauty of the Land.</hi> For is there a King in his <hi>Beauty?</hi> then why do ſuch an one endeavour to pluck away from the eyes of a Nation the moſt glorious ſight that can be beheld? What would ſuch people have? when will they be contented? wherein ſhall they find ſatisfaction? is there any thing upon earth, which can keep them long quiet? for except they would have their own wills, be Lords of all Titles, Procuratours for all general affairs, Dictatours to rule all by themſelves, hold the helm of States in their hands, order Gods Providence, hold no Crown fit to be worn, but that which their well-guiding hands ſhall ſet on, be Supreme, and Kings themſelves, can they deſire to be more happy? Do they conteſt with God, becauſe he hath made a people ſo bleſſed? may not God ſay to them, as he doth in the Goſpel? <hi>Is thine eye evil, becauſe mine is good?</hi> For if they had not evil eyes, and evil heads, and evil hearts, and evil hands, they would never thus quarrel with Gods will, and wiſdome, and goodneſſe. What? are they weary of a Banquet? doth a calm offend them? is Sun-ſhine grievous to them? is a gemme troubleſome to them to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy? is a King in his <hi>Beauty</hi> vexations to them to ſee? alas poor ſick eyes, and litigious, refractary ſpirits, it is pity that ye were not all Secretaries of State, and that God did not ſend his Decrees to you to have your pregnant approbation. But this is mans turbulent, murmuring nature, that the beſt things are divers times the greateſt grievances, and that they which cannot govern themſelves muſt
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:100932:29"/>be continually querulous againſt Rulers. <hi>Ye take too much upon you</hi> ſaid <hi>Corah</hi> and his complices. Num. 16.3. <hi>Why hast ſerved us thus?</hi> ſaid the men of Ephraim to <hi>Gideon,</hi> and <hi>they chode with him ſharply.</hi> Judges 8.1. <hi>How ſhall he ſave us? and they deſpiſed him, and brought him no preſents.</hi> 1 Sam. 10.27. <hi>See thy matters are good and righteous, but there is no man deputed of the King to hear thee, oh that I were made a Judge in the Land, that every man which hath any matter, or controverſy might come to me, and I might do him Juſtice,</hi> ſaid <hi>Abſalon</hi> of <hi>Davids</hi> Government, 2. Sam. 15.3, 4. So that there is no Government, or Governour will pleaſe many men.<note place="margin">Plut. in Apoph.</note> Thus <hi>Ariſtodemus</hi> liked not the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Antigonus</hi> King of Macedonia, becauſe he was too libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, and the Court of <hi>Lyſimachus</hi> muſt be found fault with, becauſe there were none but <hi>diſyllabic,</hi> men with two ſyllables in their names (as <hi>Bythes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Athen. l. <hi>14.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Paris,</hi> &amp;c.) which had all the authority under him. <hi>Augustus Caeſar,</hi> becauſe he would never call the Praetorian bands fellow-ſoldiers, but ſoldiers (he never deſiring to make uſe of them, but when he was conſtrained) and becauſe he was ſo li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beral to the Citizens,<note place="margin">Macrob. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> and reſpective to the Senatours, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted much in ſinging, he was by <hi>Timagenes, Labeo,</hi> and <hi>Pollio</hi> and ſome others not thought fit to govern. So we have a genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of men ſtill left amongſt us that are apt to aſperſe the moſt meriting Prince, and not onely to ſtretch out their ſlanderous tongues, but their barbarous hands to pull him down; what ſavage wars have we had in this Nation waged in a blind rage, and not onely till the Land hath been ſprinkled with the bloud of her Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, but the Scaffold died with the Bloud of a moſt Innocent King? and this King-killing will be a Trade, if God from Heaven do not ſtrike an horrour, and dread of ſuch an impious act into their hearts. Oh ye wild Furies then conſider what ye have done, conſider what ye are about to do; Chriſtians ye are not, are ye men? what ye live in a Country, to appal a Country? to trouble her peace? waſt her treaſure? to deprive her of the light of her eyes? what is a family without a Maſter? what is a Kingdom without a King? Repent then for what ye have done, and do not think that a pardon is eaſily gotten; an Act of Indemnity may ſave your necks, but it muſt be an high expiatory Act that muſt ſave your ſouls; If <hi>David</hi> wept ſo bitterly for the murther of one <hi>Uriah,</hi>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:100932:29"/>ye had need have <hi>Davids</hi> penitential teares, and his penitential Pſalm for the thouſands that ye have ſlaine, and eſpecially for the murther of that one King that was worth ten thouſand of us. Ye have immodeſt cheekes if they have no ſhame, ye have flinty hearts if they have no remorſe, as ſtupidly as ye paſſe over ſuch a guilt, it is well if eighteen years repentance, nay a ſtrict penance of your whole lives can procure you a reconciliation in Heaven; there is a great difference between a diſpenſation of your partial Prophets, and juſtification at the white Throne of the Judge of quick and dead. What then? have ye ſtill dry eyes? and will ye ſhed no tears? yes, ſprings might guſh out of the rocks, hearts of adamant might cleave aſunder. <hi>Ahab</hi> might go ſoftly, and <hi>Judas</hi> out of horrour of conſcience might cry out <hi>I have ſinned in betraying Innocent Blood.</hi> If ye have not <hi>Ahabs</hi> conſternations, and Judas'<hi>s</hi> cryes, ye will have frights, and ſtings, and yelles enough in Hell. There is yet a means of attonement, an opportunity of healing, if ye be not of the number of them, which <hi>have hearts that cannot repent.</hi> Rom. 2.5. try what Suppliants, and penitents ye can be, ye had need go water every Camp, where ye have fought your bloody Battles, and to moiſten the ground of that Scaffold where that execrable murther was committed with ſhowres of ſalt water. And if ye can work out your peace raiſe not another war in your conſciences, if ye can be <hi>made whole ſin no more.</hi> Your ſwords are ſheathed, draw them not again; ye are ſent home quietly, hang not out a new flag of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance. What have ye to do to be Stateſ-men? follow your callings, and look to take the enormities out of your own lives, what are ye to meddle with errours of Government? no, leave politicks to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, neither ye, nor your great Maſters have any thing to doe with a Kings actions, except it be by way of humble adviſe. For, <hi>Where the word of a King is there is power, and who ſhall ſay to him, what dost thou?</hi> Eccleſ. 8.3. What have Subjects then to deſcant upon a Kings Government, as if they were his Supra-viſours, and Guardians? The Lawes of God allow no ſuch authority, and it is but a State inchantment to ſay that the fundamental Lawes of this Kingdome have impowred any to call a King to a violent account. He hath onely God for his Judge, and all the people under him as Liege-men. Beware therefore of thoſe puling groanes, oh here is a ſick State, come along with us to adminiſter phyſick, if
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:100932:30"/>the King will not frame up ſuch a Government as we deſire, we will teach him how to rule by the edge of our ſwords. Theſe are not Phyſicians, but cut-throats. God hath allowed no ſuch Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celſians in a Kingdom to cure a Kings diſtempers. For if a King may not be provoked to wrath, he may not be ſo far provoked as to fight for his life; if he may not be ſpoken evil of, or curſed, his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladies are not to be remedied by cutting off his head. This is rather to be Executioners, then State-Doctours; I never yet read, that there could be a Lictor, or a Spiculator, or a Carniſex for a King. Let the greateſt Subjects then buſy themſelves in preparing Lawes for the Commonwealth, and not in preſcribing rules to a King; in remedying the grievances of the Country, and not in avenging grievances, which may be ſuſpected by a King; in binding the people to obedience, and not in bringing a King to account; For they are but Subjects, and they cannot adde to themſelves one cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit above their ſtature. If ye comply with ſuch politicians, ye do but pleaſe a company of ſeditious perſons, and incenſe the Nation in general, for ye cannot do a greater injury to your Country, nor of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer a greater indignity, and violence to true Patriots, then to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb the peace of the Land, and to ſtrike at a King. For the Kings ſafety is the Kingdomes Triumph, <hi>The Nation hath no greater joy then to ſee the King in his Beauty. Thine eyes ſhall ſet the King in his Beauty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Sixthly, this ſerves <hi>to exhort all good Subjects not to disfigure the face of Majeſty,</hi> for if the <hi>Beauty</hi> of a King be the brighteſt thing, that a Nations eyes can be fixed upon, then what a dark Kingdom is there when a King does not ſhine out in Royal Splendour? If every one would have his right, that the Cotrager, and Commoner would not loſe his Country tenure, nor the man of noble bloud, and honourable family would not loſe his peerage, then why ſhould not the King have his <hi>Jura regalia, his Crown-rights?</hi> I confeſſe the Propriety of the Subject, and plead for it, but I find likewiſe, and am an Advocate, that there may be <hi>Hammelech Melech, The Right of a King,</hi> 1 Sam. 8.11. it is a Right of great antiquity, no fundamental Law can vy Seniority with it; no, <hi>mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum festorum Jovis glandes comedit,</hi> it doth derive the pedigree 4. <hi>Nannaſo,</hi> there are <hi>antiquiores dipththerae</hi> to be brought for it, indeed it is as ancient as the Inſtitution, now the word do natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:100932:30"/>ſignify Right, &amp; it is but Metaphorically tranſlated Manner, as <hi>Buxtorfius,</hi> and <hi>Pagnine</hi> declare, if it be a Right then it muſt continue, as long as the original Hebrew hold. The Text will not periſh, nor the Title. It is the Kings Right, but it is Gods Deſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Charter for the Crown. I do not ſay the King ſhould have all, I know to the contrary, but I ſay that the King ſhould have his own, none ought to ſay to the contrary, eſpecially, when it is <hi>Jus divinum,</hi> a Gods-right. The Kings Right being ſetled up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Scripture it is firmer, then if it were bottomed upon the beſt State-groundſel. Some ſay, that this is onely meant, when God doth give a King in his wrath, but I ſay then that they are in wrath, for there is a great diſtance of time between <hi>Samuel,</hi> and <hi>Hoſee,</hi> and between <hi>Saul,</hi> and <hi>Jeroboam.</hi> Kingdomes may have their particular Conſtitutions in accidental things which do belong to a King, but not in the eſſence of a King, eſpecially not againſt the eſſence of a divine Inſtitution. Let all the juſt reverence that may be be given to humane Lawes, but ſtill let Scripture be ſacred, and inviolable, or elſe what have we left that is ſtable, &amp; infallible? The handmaid muſt not rule the Lady, or the ſtar out-ſhine the Sun, all the Sages of a Land muſt not be wiſer, then the Oracles of God.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Virg. <hi>3.</hi> Aeneid.</note> —Parcius iſtis.</l>
               <l>Cedamus Phoebo &amp; moniti meliora ſequamur.</l>
            </q>
            <p>A Prophet that hath underſtanding in the viſions of God is not to be believed in this, no, <hi>If an Angel from Heaven ſhould come, and preach otherwiſe let him be accurſed.</hi> Galath. 1.8. Well then, what is the <hi>Beauty</hi> of a King? what but his power? Take a King without power, and what is he, but a Ghoſt without life, a meer Phantaſme, and Apparition? How can he do any thing that is Kingly, either in ſetling Religion, protecting the Church, adminiſtring juſtice, making leagues, drawing his people to Humiliation for their ſins, in maintaining the liberties of his people at home, or propulſing the violences, and affronts of Adverſaries abroad? no, he muſt ſit by with tears in his eyes, and deplore all exorbitancies, and ſad acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, but not be able to remedy them; he hath a ſympathy, but he hath no Soveraignty; he hath a will, but he hath no power; he hath a face but he hath no Beauty in it. A Kings authority then is the true Majeſty of a King, till he can command like a King, he doth but perſonate a King. Oh then that the policy of many men
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:100932:31"/>is but to deſigne againſt the power, that their chiefeſt drift is not in honouring and obeying a King, but in reſtraining and regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating a King, that when their purſes are empty, then they fill them by a Crown-quarrel; that when their high parts are not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, then they will be obſerved to be Maſter-wits in ſeeking to maſter authority; and to ſilence ſuch a Mutiner, a Challenger by many a good King muſt be preferred, when many a loyal Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion of as good endowments and better worth muſt ſtand upon low ground, and this popular Eare-wig creep to his deſired height. But away with theſe new dogmatizing principles of State-magick, whereby Kings are conjured into politicians Circles, or confined to their auguſt limits. This may be a Science, but I am ſure it is none of the liberal Sciences. It is a pitiful thing, when a King come to be tutoured under ſuch Pedagogues, he is then rather a Diſciple, a pupil then a King, for he muſt do nothing, but what is preſcribed him, nor order any thing but according to commenſurations. And this is rather Geometry, then Monarchy, or to make a Mathemati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal, rather then a Majeſtical King. Let the people have their birth-rights, Liberties, Priviledges, but let not liberty eat up Royalty, nor birth-right, Crown-right, nor priviledge Prerogative, for then the judgement in Aegypt is fallen upon the Land, that <hi>the lean kine have eaten up the fat,</hi> and what then but a famine can be expected? The people may be amiable, but the King hath no <hi>Beauty,</hi> or the ſoul of the Kings power is defunct, and by a Pythagorean tranſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gration is paſt into the body of the people. And how will Natives then diſregard ſuch a King? and how will Forreigners inſult over him? he ſhall be able to act nothing neither at home, nor abroad. The thick ſmoak in the form of a cloud which was raiſed by one burning of beanes might more terrify <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth,<note place="margin">Iovius l. <hi>37.</hi> hiſt. Plut. in Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dro.</note> and <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis</hi> the firſt at <hi>Villafrank,</hi> they thinking that a Navy of the Turks had been coming, and the very dead ſtatue of <hi>Alexander</hi> at the Temple of <hi>Apollo</hi> at <hi>Delphos</hi> might make <hi>Caſſander</hi> ſooner trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble then the preſence of a King will beget awe or reverence in ſuch a Nation. But ſome will ſay that Kings ought to have Counſellers, and he muſt be guided by them. Ought, and muſt are high words. It is convenient I confeſſe that Kings ſhould have Counſellers, for in the multitude of Counſellers there is health (<hi>Salomon</hi> the wiſe was not without them) but then theſe Counſellours muſt not be Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellers,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:100932:31"/>the King muſt be the Head of the Counſel, a King muſt not be ſubjected to their excentrical humours (if any ſuch things ſhould happen) or to their ſelf-willed, and ſelf-ended aymes, for theſe ſhould then be rather projectours then Counſellours, or Dicta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, then Directours; all the <hi>Beauty</hi> ſhould then be in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours cheeks, and not in the Kings-face. Let there be as many Counſellours then as ye will, but ſtill let the King have the liberty of election, to accept, or reject what in his Princely wiſdome he thinks fitting, for conſtraining adviſe belongs rather to headſtrong, ſurly Subjects, then to true Counſellours. A King no doubt may as well refuſe ill counſel, as ill meat, ill weather, ill lodging. Bad company is dangerous, and ſo likewiſe is bad counſel. Is a King bound to walk in the dark? to take receipts of all Empiricks? to ſail with all winds? to go out of the way, if his guides miſlead him? no, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Lucian: in Aſin. Plut. in Themi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoc.</note> It were better to run back in the middle of the way, then to run wrong. That Counſel may be followed there muſt be <hi>ſancta penetralia juſtitiae, the holy inwards of justice.</hi> How is a King at liberty if his judgement be not free? his captived perſon were ſomething like to his captived reaſon. <hi>Non per regulas juris communis tenetur ſequi eorum conſilium,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pet. Greg. de rep. l. <hi>24.</hi> c. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>quos adhibet conſilio,</hi> The King is not tyed by the rules of common juſtice to follow their Counſel, whom he doth admit to Counſel, no ordinary Client is limited to this. How is it <hi>the Kings honour to ſearch out a thing.</hi> Prov. 25.2. if the Kings heart muſt ly in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mens breſts? why do <hi>David</hi> ſay, <hi>Give thy judgements to the King.</hi> Pſ. 72.1. if all the judgements of a Land lay in Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours lips, or the King hath no commands of himſelf, but by depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation? No good King will refuſe Counſel, no wiſe King will yoak himſelf to Counſel. The King might then make himſelf a ſlave, the Church a vaſſal, and the Kingdom a Bondman. Then the Land hath loſt her Liberty, and he himſelf may loſe his Crown. For though noble Counſellours diſdain to give any Counſel but according to honour and conſcience, yet there are a company of pragmatical Sages, that will be <hi>Balaams, Jonadabs,</hi> old <hi>Achito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phels,</hi> or young <hi>Rehoboams</hi> Counſellours. If the King then be neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitated to the wits, or wills of all Counſellours, where is his Scepter, and Broad Seale? Let there be then Majeſty in Kings, moderation in Counſellours; Soveraignty in Kings, ſobriety in Counſellours;
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:100932:32"/>dominion in Kings, devoir in Counſellours. For if the King be to <hi>ſit in the Throne,</hi> and he is <hi>the Law-giver</hi> of the Nation, and peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple be to <hi>ſeek the Kings face,</hi> and to liſten to the <hi>Divine ſentence that is to come out of his lips,</hi> if he be to <hi>ſit as chief,</hi> and to <hi>dwell like a King in an Army,</hi> if he be to <hi>ſend forth the Decrees,</hi> and <hi>Nations be to bow down before him,</hi> if young men ought to hide themſelves from him, and old men ought to ariſe, and ſtand up, if the voices of Princes ought to be ſtayed in his preſence, and after his words they ought not to reply, if all the Land ought to wait for him as for the raine, and to open their mouthes for him as for the latter raine, then ſurely the beſt Councel, the great Councel of a Kingdom is not circumſcriptive to a King. No, good Counſellours know better fealty, &amp; bad Counſellours ought to leave off this exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liency. Let <hi>Magna Charta</hi> then be preſerved, and the petition of Right have all the right that is in it, but let the <hi>Maxima Charta,</hi> and the preſcription of Kings Right be thought on with them, and above them; for it is the Elder Brother, and of the Bloud Royal, and ought to weare the Crown before all others. If then the honour of God, or the fear of his Lawes, the Image of God in a Kings fore-head, or the Scepter of God in his Hand, a Kings Royal Ornaments, or a Kings Royal Office, the advancement of Religion, or the protection of the innocent, the obedience of Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects at home, or the dread of Forraigners abroad, the duty that ye require from your children, or the reverence that ye expect from Inferiours, the peace of the Kingdom, or the proſperity of the Kingdom carry any authority with you, let the laſt word be ſpoken, that may tend to the diſparagement of the Kings dignity, and the laſt arrow be ſhot that may be levelled to the diminution of his power, let us fill his Coffers with Gold, and his heart with confidence, let us end all enmity in unanimity, &amp; change all fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe into fidelity, let us fight no more againſt Kings, but fold our armes in ſubjection, let us all fall at the Kings feet, and vow never again to ſtrike at his head, let us join no more battels, but join hands, weep that we have been ſuch enemies, and ſmile that we are become ſuch friends; let us rejoyce that we have gotten at home the Father of our Country, &amp; be glad that we are coming home to our Mother Church; let it comfort us that the King hath brought Biſhops along with him to reſtore us to our firſt Faith, and Judges
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:100932:32"/>to ſettle us in our old inheritances; oh let it delight us that we are come to our wits, and begin to remember that we are Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and that the malignity of the Church-fever is ſpent, and that we begin to look upon one another as Fellow-Profeſſours. Let us ſay we will go together to the Kings Court, and go together to the Kings Chappel, that we will join together in allegiance, and join together in worſhip; adore the ſame God, and knit our hearts to the ſame King. All this is for the Kings honour, and if we will have a King let us grudge him no honour. Let it be our ambition to ſtrive, that we may be the moſt devoted people to a King, to be the <hi>Nation of Loyalty, the Iſland that will ſet up a magnificent King, that no Subjects upon earth ſhall pay ſuch Homage to a Soveraign, as the Engliſh Protestant. Oh let us adorn the Protestant, and grandize the King!</hi> For to make the King great, it is to make our ſelves happy, and honourable, for there is no greater delight and dignity to a Country then to have a King exalted, the bleſſing and <hi>Beauty</hi> of a Kingdom is to ſee a <hi>King in his Beauty,</hi> for <hi>Thine eyes ſhall ſee the King in his Beauty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Well in concluſion let me bring home the joy of the Text to our own hearts, and preſent the ſight in the Text to our own eyes; The propheſy was firſt fulfilled upon Jeruſalem, and we have had it in as memorable, and miraculous a way ſeconded, and doubled upon us. We have been Spectatours of Wonders, Fathers to their children may relate them, whatſoever dolorous things for a while afflicted our eyes, yet theſe ſad Objects are removed, and we have beheld thoſe things which are pleaſant to the eyes, <hi>Our eyes have ſeen the King in his Beauty.</hi> Had not our King as fierce enemies, as <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah?</hi> yes <hi>Senacherib</hi> ranged over this Country, and made all the Land to tremble, that hammer of the earth daſhed all in pieces, for he, and his <hi>Rabſhakehs,</hi> and Rabſariſſes, and Tartans made a Land that was like the Garden of <hi>Eden</hi> like a deſolate wilderneſſe, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther high-wayes, nor high Rulers, fields nor Forreſts, Cities nor Caſtles were ſecure, but our wards and our woods, our heritages and our honours, our labours and our lawes, our reputations and our religion, our beaſts and our beds, our tillage and our Tables, our Tabernacles and our Temples, our backs and our necks were ſubject to the fury of our Adverſaries, for what were we but an harraſſed Land, a plundered Nation, a ſequeſtred people? Our
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:100932:33"/>enemies ruled over us with rigour, and made our lives bitter unto us, Cities were turned into heaps, and the houſes of Ivory periſhed, the ſhield of the mighty was vilely caſt away, and nothing amongſt us but waſtes and groanes, chaines and gibbets, all the mirth of the Land was gone, and the very Songs of the Temple were turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to howlings, we even ſtood amazed under our diſaſters, and even deſpaired ever to ſee better dayes. Many a cord was let down to pluck us out of miſery, but <hi>Hic funis nihil attraxit,</hi> This rope drew nothing, many means uſed to preſerve us in the ſtorm, but <hi>Deus praevertit anchorae jactum,</hi> God prevented the caſting forth of the Anchour, ſo that</p>
            <q>— abſumpta ſalus, nec ſpes jam reſtat Iüli,</q>
            <p>All ſafety ſeemed to be taken from us, and there was no hope ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing to repair our broken fortunes, our hearts even failed us, and we were ready to ly down in our confuſion, for when any gave us comfortable words to expect yet happier, we accounted them.</p>
            <q>— velut aegri ſomnia vana,</q>
            <p>As ſick mens dreams, and gave no other but a kind of diffident anſwer. <hi>Alas who ſhall live when God doth theſe things!</hi> Num. 24.23. Yet how hath God cleared the Land of <hi>Senacherib?</hi> &amp; ſaved us by a mighty deliverance? <hi>Senacherib</hi> is vaniſhed, and <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> deſired <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> admired <hi>Hezekiah, Hezekiah</hi> the King of high preſervations, <hi>Hezekiah</hi> the King of conſpicuous qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions doth appear, we may carve the whole Text, graven in capital Letters, golden Characters, and celeſtial impreſſes upon our hearts, for, <hi>We have ſeen, and we have ſeen a King,</hi> and <hi>We have ſeen a King in his Beauty.</hi> Oh Heaven hath preſented to us this ſight, this is the <hi>Object of Miracles. We may draw nigh, and ſee this great ſight.</hi> Exod. 3.2. <hi>Hath this been done before, or in the dayes of your Fathers?</hi> Joel 1.2. no there hath not been the like, neither ſhall there to many generations, we may count it as one of <hi>the chief of the wayes of God;</hi> for a King that could not enter the Land, nor ſafely ſet his foot upon any corner of the Nation, now with <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> he may <hi>ſee the Land afar off,</hi> and walk upon the length and bredth of the Land. <hi>Who hath heard ſuch a thing? who hath ſeen ſuch things?</hi> Iſ. 66.8. doubtleſſe that in Num. 23.23. may be applyed to us, <hi>According to this time it ſhall be ſaid of Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:100932:33"/>and Iſrael, what hath God wrought?</hi> what? an incredible, an ineffable, and an invaluable thing. <hi>Bleſſed be the Omnipotent God, and bleſſed be his potent Champion,</hi> which hath made the Land happy in the ſight of a King, &amp; in the ſight of ſuch a King; I ſay of ſuch a King, who cometh to us with a right Title; one Uſurper more would have quite broke the heart-ſtrings of the Nation; &amp; with the right Religion; a Papiſt, or a Phanatick would have after ſo many factions &amp; fractions ſhivered the Church into nothing but ſherds; &amp; with the right Princely endowments, who hath in him a treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of moralities, &amp; may be a pattern to all the Princes of his time for true virtue. An Hereditary King, an Orthodoxe King, a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat King, what can the eye of the Nation look upon with more ſatisfaction? no, <hi>Our eyes do ſee a King in his Beauty;</hi> we do ſee him ſo in his perſonal Beauty, and God forbid but we ſhould give him all the National Beauty that may be. Confeſſe his right, and give him his right, welcome him home with melody, and beſtow Majeſty upon him; make him as great, as he doth deſire to make us mighty; we were never happy before he came, we are unhappy, if we know not how happy we are ſince his coming, he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed us out of errour, out of bondage, out of deſpair. <hi>O Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing King!</hi> Let us not ſerve him now as the Iſraelites ſerved <hi>Moſes,</hi> who were ever groaning till they had a Deliverer, and ever mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muring after they had a Deliverer. No, let our joy in him be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to the comforts he hath brought along with him; and our peerleſſe eſteem of him be anſwerable to his prizeleſſe worth; Conſider his devout Heart, and his divine Lips, what zeal he doth bear to the truth, and what hatred he doth carry to an Oath, how he hath preſerved his Religion amongſt the Jeſuits, and is come to his Subjects to tell them what a Proteſtant he is; conſider his chaſt eye, and his ſober Palate, his ſoft bowels and his juſt hand; how he is fragrant with almſdeeds, and doth ſhine in wiſdome; how he was patient under afflictions, and is humble in proſperity; how he hath forgiven his enemies, and is daily preferring his Friends; how the whole Land doth not exceed him in Candour, nor the whole earth in valour; conſider what he hath done for your conſciences, what for your liberties, what for your Lawes, what for learning, what for a flouriſhing trade, and what for a ſetled peace; conſider if he be not the prime man that could have comforted you, if he
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:100932:34"/>be not the onely man which could have made you happy, and will ye open your eyes, and not open your lips? give him your accla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations, and not give him your affections? ſhall Engliſh-men have the beſt King, and be the worſt Subjects? be the ferventeſt Deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers of a King, and the fickleſt Reverencers of a King? what ſtill ſquint-eyed, rank-breathed, half-hearted? ſtill Cenſurers, Malecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, Mutiners? Send for <hi>Senacherib</hi> then again, if <hi>Hezekiah</hi> do not pleaſe you. Oh the variable, and unſtable ſpirits of men! what Scepticks are we in politicks? what Criticks in Government? we do but deſire to enjoy a Bleſſing, and then complaint of wants; we do but deſire to ſee a King, and then ſpy faults; we are glutted with a taſte, and heavy-eyed with a ſight; take a guſt, and ſhut up our lips; ſtare a little, and then turn away our eyes; pleaſe our fancies, and affect no longer; delight our ſelves with a gaze and then diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine. But oh beloved were we ſick for a King, and are any now weary of him? no, very <hi>Eſau</hi> me think ſhould fall upon the neck of ſuch a <hi>Jacob,</hi> &amp; weep at the meeting; very Shimeis mouth ſhould leave foming, and he ſhould fall down at the feet of ſuch a <hi>David,</hi> and ask pardon when he ſees him returning; the moſt heart-brent enemies that ever the King had methink ſhould give over all their ſpleen and rancour, and admire his clemency and magnify his graces. <hi>If theſe ſhould hold their peace the ſtones would ſpeak,</hi> ſo if theſe will not prize ſuch a King, very Infidels would honour him. Oh therefore let every Subject in the Realme know their own King, their lawfull King, and give him cordial reſpect, faithfull obedience, and an eminency of affection. Let Noble-men love him, for as he is the Fountain of their honours, ſo he hath reſtored their honours to them; let Clergy-men love him, for he is a Sanctuary to the Sanctuary; let Judges love him, for he hath put life into the Lawes, and given them a reſurrection; let Merchants love him, for they which were ready to turn Bank-rupts, may yet again turn Bankers; let all the Land love him, for there is not a corner of the Nation, but he hath filled it with joy, and repleniſhed it with bleſſings. Well let us all gather together, &amp; weep for joy that after ſo many miſeries we live to ſee ſuch Halcyon dayes, and ſing for joy, that after ſo many diſmal ſights, we have eyes in our heads to ſee this one ſight, this onely ſight, this reviving, raviſhing ſight, even to <hi>ſee the King in his Beauty. Thine eyes ſhall ſee the King in his Beauty.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:100932:34"/>
And as we have ſeen the ſight, ſo let us not loſe the ſight, that after we have ſeen the King in his Beauty, we ſhould ſee a King in Bloud; no, if the Lawes of God, and the Mercy of the King can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not quench Fire-brands, but there ſhould happen to be new flames, new wars, let all faithful Subjects be diſmembred rather then one Member of his Sacred Perſon ſhould be wounded, and let every loyal Hand in the three Nations be cut off, rather then the traite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous hand ſhould touch his Royal Head. For if we ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived again of the King in his Beauty, the Beauty of the Land is gone, and the miſery of the Land will renew, we ſhall have old plundring, and rifling, and ſequeſtring, and impriſoning, and braining, &amp; gibbetting again; if the King ſuffer, let not us think to ſcape ſcot-free; if the King dye, let not us think to live long after him, no, let us reſolve of a general Maſſacre, and a Funeral of the whole Nation. Now that King and Kingdom may be ſecure, let us make ſure of him that is the Keeper of Iſrael, oh how ſafe might we be under his everlaſting Armes! <hi>He would be the ſheild of our help, and the ſword of our excellencies.</hi> Oh therefore let us not provoke the eyes of his glory, and he will watch for our defence, let us not break his Lawes, &amp; not a bone of us ſhall be broken, let us weep out our former corruptions with tears, and ſhew our ſelves to be alive from the dead by our regenerate faces; let every Roya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſt turn the greateſt Penitent and trueſt Saint; as we account our ſelves the moſt Orthodox Profeſſours, ſo let us declare it by our mortified lives, and pure conſciences; So may we defy all the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies in the Nation, for in deſpight of all their fury and maugre all their malice, <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſhall be a quiet habitation, a Tabernacle that cannot be removed, her ſtakes ſhall not be taken away, but we ſhall here long ſee a King in his Beauty, and hereafter ſee a King in his Glory, which that we may do, the Lord grant for his mercies ſake, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
